<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A divine cordiall for a devout soule Composed out of a serious discourse upon sinne against the Holy Ghost: as it was laid open in the full nature and appendices thereof. In a sermon preached at Taunton in the county of Somerset, upon Monday, April 4. 1653. In the assize week. By William Sclater, Doctor in Divinity, now preacher of the Word of God in Broadstreet, London.</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62376</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S916A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222484</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833651</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833651</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62376)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2177:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A divine cordiall for a devout soule Composed out of a serious discourse upon sinne against the Holy Ghost: as it was laid open in the full nature and appendices thereof. In a sermon preached at Taunton in the county of Somerset, upon Monday, April 4. 1653. In the assize week. By William Sclater, Doctor in Divinity, now preacher of the Word of God in Broadstreet, London.</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons, and are to be sould by William Hope at the Blew Anchor behind the Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John V, 16-17 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Holy Spirit --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38129:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38129:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>DIVINE</hi> CORDIALL FOR A Devout Soule.</p>
            <p>Compoſed out of a ſerious Diſcourſe upon the Sinne againſt the HOLY GHOST: As it was laid open in the full Nature and Appendices thereof.</p>
            <p>In a SERMON Preached at <hi>Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> upon <hi>Monday, April</hi> 4. 1653. In the Aſſize Week.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM SCLATER, <hi>Doctor in Divinity,</hi> Now Preacher of the Word of God in <hi>Broadſtreet, LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 12.31, 32.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wherefore I ſay unto you, all manner of Sin and Blaſphemy ſhall be forgiven unto men: But the Blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſhall not be forgiven unto men. And whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſpeaketh a word againſt the Son of man, it ſhall be forgiven him: But whoſoever ſpeaketh againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> it ſhall not be forgiven him, neither in this World, nor in the World to come.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons,</hi> and are to be ſould by <hi>William Hope</hi> at the Blew <hi>Anchor</hi> behind the <hi>Exchange.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:38129:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38129:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFULL <hi>George Luttrell</hi> of <hi>Dunſter</hi>-Caſtle, Eſq; High Sheriffe of the County of <hi>Somerſet:</hi> All true felicity.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon (ſolid, I hope, though not polite, or trim enough, perhaps, for this age) as it was by an unexpected providence, in a ſolemne, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Aſſembly, preached at your inſtance; now alſo, upon your motion, together with the entreaties of the primeſt Auditors, drawne forth into a more generall view: It cannot but claime a double intereſt in you, both as an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Hearer (ſuch as your ſtation rendred you) and as a Patron, ſuch as its owne tenuity cannot but want: It comes to you, not that you (chiefly under ſo great a ſurfet of the Preſſe) need it, but that it needs you: The honour of whoſe worthy family and Progenitors, it hath ſtill been to be <hi>Mecae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates Scholarium,</hi> and your Caſtle (like the old <hi>Parnaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus</hi>) as it were an Academy for learning, and learned men: It's written of <hi>Abel</hi> (righteous by Gods owne teſtimony of him) that <hi>being dead, he yet ſpeaketh,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>is yet ſpoken of;</hi> his exemplary piety carrying with it a kinde of Vocall Oratory to perſwade even the ages to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to imitation, that whileſt the luſtre of his graces ſparkle in the lives of ſucceſſors, his memory cannot but be perpetuated: And long may whatſoever was eximious in our Anceſtors, find ſtill a continuation in your ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But indeed, that being properly a mans<note n="*" place="margin">Sed genus, &amp; proavos, &amp; quae nen feci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ipſi vix ea [noſtra] voco—<hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </note> owne in vertue, which is perſonall; your owne merit being (as I queſtion not) copious, may claime a Panegyricke, as ample; to the ſound of things commendable your name and actions (like <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niſons in Muſick) anſwere, and (out of no long acquaintance) I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb facs="tcp:38129:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>your modeſty to adorne your endowments; it reſembles ſhadowing in the Art of Limning, which turnes extreamly to the advantage of the Limner, by ſetting off the excellency of his Penſill: Yet however you delight not to be praiſed to your ſelf, notwithſtanding your pious ingenuity will conſtantly have eye unto things praiſe-worthy. It was a goodly ſight to behold Gods Tabernacle, and <hi>Davids</hi> Palace ſituate together on the ſame <hi>Sion;</hi> ſo is it to ſee Goodneſſe and Greatneſſe like thoſe living Creatures, and thoſe wheels (in<note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>Ezekiel</hi>) to move, and to be lift up together: When all is done, godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the greateſt<note n="‖" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.6.</note> gaine, and religious practice the higheſt<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> honour: Whileſt this is your aime, your Name ſhall become as ſome precious Ointment poured out, your ſelfe, your vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſort, and all your relations, ſhall be bleſſed out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with the exuberancies of Gods both hands, you ſhall aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the reputation of your houſe, and the already purchaſed eſtimation of your Countrey: If my weake endeavours in this preſent Sermon may prove any furtherance this way, I have my deſire, as, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Yours, To be Commanded in the Lord. WILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:38129:3"/>
            <head>WHAT THE SINNE Againſt the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> is.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 JOHN 5.16, 17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>There is a Sin unto death: I doe not ſay that he ſhall pray for it.</p>
                  <p>All <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſſe is Sin, and there is a Sinne not unto death.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not in my purpoſe, nor came it at all within the Compaſſe of my Thoughts (Right Honourable, and Beloved) when I came late, the other evening, unto this<note n="*" place="margin">Tanton.</note> 
               <hi>Towne</hi> (ſo well ſpoken of for Religion, and diſcreet zeale for Gods Ordinances) to become a Speaker here, this morning, on ſo ſolemn an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Yet ſith the divine providence hath ſo diſpoſed, I willingly ſubmit thereto, chooſing rather to expoſe my weakneſſe to the pious candor of this ſo intelligent Auditory, than to decline ſo faire an occaſion, to bring ſome glory to God, in the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mat. 25.16.</note> uſe of my Talent, after my<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rom. 12.3. 2 Cor. 10.13.</note> meaſure.</p>
            <p>And ſo, without farther Apology, I addreſſe my ſelfe to my Text; for the clearer explanation whereof, it may not be amiſſe to reflect a little upon the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Context, and the Circumſtances thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Context."/> The Apoſtle from the fourteenth verſe to the laſt, in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38129:4"/>this Chapter, ſheweth us (as the Diamonds ſet in the Rings of theſe three Epiſtles) ſundry eminent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imious Priviledges belonging to the regenerate ſons and daughters of God: ſuch are,
<list>
                  <item>1. Aſſurance of audience in Prayers, provided they order their devotions according to his will, <hi>ver.</hi> 14.</item>
                  <item>2. Immunity from Apoſtacy.</item>
                  <item>3. Knowledge of Regeneration.</item>
                  <item>4. Certaine and infallible perſwaſion of the truth of myſteries of Faith, Knowledge of the True God, and Union with him in Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 20.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And verſe the ſixteenth he amplifies that Bleſſing of being heard in prayers by extent of it; that priviledg appertaining to them. Not only as it may ſerve for ſupply of their owne perſonall wants, but alſo as it may benefit and advantage others; we ſay indeed in our Creed, <hi>I believe in God,</hi> to denote, that it muſt be our owne particular faith that muſt ſave us; but in our Lords Prayer, <hi>Our father, which art in Heaven,</hi> to imply that our Prayers may further the good of others beſides our ſelves; wherefore S. <hi>John</hi> withall inſinuates an Exhortation, that as they had received this favour of God to be heard in their requeſts both for themſelves and others, ſo they would improve, and uſe the ſame, not alone for themſelves, but likewiſe to the help and behoofe of others. Wherein are theſe obſervables.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The duty exhorted unto, <hi>Prayer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Object of this Duty, with a limitation, <hi>A Brother not ſinning unto death.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Reaſon, from the profitable effect, <hi>He ſhall give him life.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the latter end of the ſixteenth verſe he ſubjoynes the reaſon of that limitation; as if he had ſaid, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell not, that I interpoſe that reſtraint, <hi>A Brother ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning not unto death; for there is a ſin unto death, for which no man may pray:</hi> And then is added a prolepſis, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>Is not all unrighteouſneſſe ſin? all ſin deadly?</hi> to which he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38129:4"/>anſwers, 1. By Conceſſion, yes, <hi>All unrighteouſneſſe is ſin.</hi> 2. By an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or correction, but <hi>there is a ſin not unto death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This the Context, and order of the words. My pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſcourſe, wherewith I ſhall now entertaine your patience, ſhall be confined to the Reaſon of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Limitation, forementioned, namely, the ſin which is here ſaid by the Apoſtle to be unto death. A difficult queſtion, and ſo difficult, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t fortè nulla major,</hi> as S.<note n="(c)" place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Ser. 11. de verb. Dom.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> proteſteth, <hi>That ſcarſly is there any one found more in all holy writ;</hi> this being a ſin which is rarely, if at all to be deprehended, or diſcovered by man in this life.</p>
            <p>I ſhall proceed herein after this order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Endeavour to open the nature of it, what it is, or wherein it conſiſteth.</item>
               <item>2. To unfold the reaſon of the ſtile, or titles that are given it in the Scriptures.</item>
               <item>3. The dangerous iſſue, and effect of the ſame.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I begin with the conſideration of the Nature of it; and ſhall proceed therein, as Rhetoricians ſpeake, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, firſt, removing the erroneous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions both ancient, and modern hereabout; and then, ſet downe the poſitive Truth.</p>
            <p>Saint<note n="(d)" place="margin">S. <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> l. 1. c. 9. De Paenit.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> acquaints us of the <hi>Novatian</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques of old, who by ſins unto Death, that is, ſuch ſins as are mortall in the event, underſtood all ſins that are committed againſt Knowledge and Conſcience, voluntarily after Baptiſme; and to men ſo ſinning they intercluded the hope, and denyed the benefit of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan.</hi> l. 2. c. 59.</note> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: But all this not more uncomfortably, than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundly: for, beſides what we find in S.<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyprian.</hi> De lapſis.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and other ancient Fathers of the Church, touching the reſtoring of relapſed Chriſtians, who having fallen through fear, under the rage and violence of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Perſecutions, were, notwithſtanding, upon their <hi>Exomologeſis,</hi> and teſtimony given of their Repentance, and deſire of reſtitution, admitted againe into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38129:5"/>of the Church: We know that <hi>Moſes</hi> prayed for the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſinning voluntarily, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.11. ſo alſo <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23. and S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> Acts 7.59, 60. and their prayers were heard: We read likewiſe of ſome in <hi>Pergamus,</hi> even in this Apoſtle S. <hi>John's</hi> owne time, who (after Calling) held the hatefull Doctrine of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> who yet were again invited unto Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.16. and by that means came within the number of ſuch as might be prayed for.</p>
            <p>Among the Moderns, are the Romiſh Impoſters, for the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> on this place, give this ſenſe; <hi>If any ſin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death,</hi> that is, commit any mortall ſin, and impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently perſiſts therein, unto death, <hi>for ſuch an one pray not,</hi> namely, ſay they, after death; and out of this place would they, by<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Pet. 3.16.</note> torturing the Text, infer their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of prayer for the dead: and their reaſon is, becauſe no one may be dehorted from praying for any ſinner, while he is living, in as much as there is hope of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and repentance for every ſinner living: But firſt, the very ground is falſe, for the Scripture ſaith expreſly, <hi>There is a ſin committed even in this life, that is not capable of pardon, neither in this life, no nor in the life to come,</hi> Mat. 12.31. Yea, it's impoſſible to ſome, even living, to be renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto repentance, the means of pardon<note n="*" place="margin">Commodiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me accipitur hic locus de peccato in ſpiritumſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum. <hi>Jo. Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard. loc. com. tom. 2. c. 24. ſ. 108.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6. Yea, we read in the<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodoret.</hi> Hiſt l. 4. c. 17.19.</note> Hiſtory of the Church, that the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians obſerving the obſtinate impenitency of that Monſter <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, made ſet prayers, not for him, but againſt his malice, and againſt him for his deſperate malice ſake; they having, happily, therein a ſpirit of extraordinary<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.10,</note> diſcerning then, as <hi>David</hi> before had a ſpirit of Prophecy, when he made impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon, and prayers againſt his adverſaries, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 109.2. As touching prayer for the dead, as, among all the variety of Sacrifices appointed for the Jewes of old, there was none at all for the dead; ſo neither hath it any precept, promiſe, or example, in all the allowed Canon of ſacred Scripture now extant. And thirdly,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38129:5"/>that this place is to be underſtood of ſuch as live, it's apparent from this very Text, becauſe no man can [<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſee] his brother ſinning after death; beſides this, even by the School-mens owne confeſſion, ſoules departed are <hi>extra ſtatum merendi, &amp; demerendi,</hi> out of a condition of meriting or demeriting by action; and if ſoules in their imaginary Purgatory, make an end of ſinning, in vaine ſhall we pray for pardon.</p>
            <p>Leaving then theſe erroneous conceipts about this ſin, come we, next, to examine the Nature of it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Orthodox judgements of Reformed Divines, well travelled in this queſtion, and regulating their reſolves herein according to the word of God.</p>
            <p>Now, we ſhall the better diſcover this, if we parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly view the ſeveral parts and branches thereof; for it is a compound ſin, conſiſting of many ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients.</p>
            <p>I ſhall draw up all under theſe heads, ſearching,
<list>
                  <item>1. What it ſuppoſeth.</item>
                  <item>2. What it implyeth.</item>
                  <item>3. What it drawes with it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Or, in other Termes, to the ſame effect.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Antecedent.</item>
               <item>2. The Concomitants.</item>
               <item>3. The Conſequents of this ſin.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt of all, the neceſſary Antecedents, or ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals of this ſin, and theſe are,
<list>
                  <item>1. Knowledge of the Goſpel, and of the truth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in revealed concerning Jeſus Chriſt, and all the rich and<note n="(i)" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> precious Promiſes of life and ſalvation, in and by him: wherefore, they are ſaid to be once enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4.<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide</hi> Haec verba expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentem opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè. <hi>Jo. Gerar.</hi> Tract. de Pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent. c. 4. ſ. 16. tom 3. loc. Com.</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to have a great meaſure of Illumination in the myſteries of the Goſpel; and againe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26. to have received the knowledge of the truth, and to have known the way of righteouſnes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. &amp; 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. to have dogmaticall faith, or doctrine of trtuh, men ignorant of the Goſpel may
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38129:6"/>ſin mortally, and unto death, yet, during that ſtate of ſimple ignorance, for want of the right means of illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, are not capable of this ſin, therefore alſo <hi>Paul,</hi> though he was a Blaſphemer, an Oppreſſor, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly<note n="(l)" place="margin">Act 26.11.</note> mad in perſecuting the way, and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Chriſt, yet was received to mercy, for what he did, he did<note n="(m)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.13.</note> ignorantly, in the time of his unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief: and therefore Divines truly judge, that howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Turks, Infidels, Pagans, periſh (without repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) everlaſtingly, through ignorance of the truth, yet ſin they not againſt the holy Ghoſt, not this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſin here ſaid to be unto death.</item>
                  <item>2. Beſides this knowledge, which happily may be occaſioned by ſome general declaration of the truth of the Goſpel; there muſt be not a confuſed apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion alone, but alſo a clear and diſtinct underſtanding, and a full conviction of the judgement, ſo that they cannot but ſee, and know, that 'tis the truth which they ſet themſelves againſt; therefore the terms, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. are remarkable, it is not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not a bare notice, and literal underſtanding of the truth, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an acknowledgement of the ſame; as they ſpake, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.16. <hi>What ſhall we doe to theſe men, for that indeed a notable miracle hath been done by them, is manifeſt to all them that dwell in</hi> Hieruſalem, <hi>and we cannot deny it.</hi> To this purpoſe is that ſaying of our Saviour, <hi>John</hi> 15.22. <hi>If I had not come, and ſpoken unto them, they had not had ſin,</hi> that is, not ſimply none, but none in compariſon; but now they have no cloak, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, no colour, or<note n="(n)" place="margin">In ſpiritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanctum pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, qui divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae veritati, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus fulgore ſic perſtringuntur, ut ignorantiam cauſari neque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, tamen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatâ malitia reſiſtunt, in hoc tantùm ut reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. <hi>Calvin Inſt. l. 3. c. 3. ſ. 22.</hi>
                     </note> pretence of plea, by way of excuſe.</item>
                  <item>3. To theſe ſome add a third degree, as a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive alſo to this ſin, and that is ſome kind of formall profeſſion of what they have entertained into their judgements; ſo <hi>Simon Magus</hi> joyned himſelfe to the Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13. ſubmitted to Baptiſme, as one (it ſeems) deſirous by that Character, and cognizance
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38129:6"/>to be known, and taken for a Chriſtian: ſome partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obedience, and reformation they yield to the truth, intermiting the practice of their old ſins, and out of ſome<note n="(o)" place="margin">Heb. 6.5.</note> taſt of the good word of God, being affected with the comforts it conteins, they take ſome fleſhly<note n="(p)" place="margin">Mat. 13.20.</note> joy therein, in hope to partake the bleſſed ſtate of Gods Children in the life to come; in which caſe S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, that they are <hi>waſhed</hi> after a ſort, <hi>from their old ſins, and have eſcaped the pollutions of the world;</hi> 2 Pet. 2.18.20. But to this third ſtep they aſcend not all, who fall into this ſin; The<note n="(q)" place="margin">Mal. 12.24</note> 
                     <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that gave firſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to our Saviour to ſpeak of it, we read not either to have reformed their errors of life, or judgement, or ſo much as to have entertained the Goſpel, and truth taught by our Saviour, into profeſſion, yet have this ſin charged upon them: and therefore me thinks its no abſurdity to ſay, there are degrees even in this ſin un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death; but knowledge, and conviction ſufficiently diſpoſeth unto this ſin. And thus far of the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Follow next the Concomitants, or thoſe things which doe accompany this ſin, or which it doth imply.</p>
            <p>Now herein are conſiderable, partly the Facts, and partly alſo the Motives of the committers of this ſame.</p>
            <p>The Facts, ſome are common to all; ſome, peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to thoſe that have higheſt diſpoſitions towards ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace: In relation to the former ſort, there is,
<list>
                  <item>1. Abnegation and denyall of the truth of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel received, againſt diſtinct<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1.32.</note> knowledge and<note n="‖" place="margin">John 8.9.</note> convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of enlightned conſcience; and this denyall uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally joyned with blaſphemy, and reproachfull, contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melious rayling againſt Oods truth, as thoſe <hi>Phariſees,</hi> Mat. 12.24. though they could not but ſee Gods po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in the miracles wrought by our Saviour, yet blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly impute thoſe mighty works of the Spirit of God, to the Prince of devils, even to <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> that is,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38129:7"/>to the Lord of Flyes, as the Hebrew word imports.</item>
                  <item>2. Oppoſing and oppugning by all means the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the truth; its noted of <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that they had made an Ordinance, that whoſoever confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or joyned himſelfe to Chriſt, he ſhould be caſt out of their Synagogue, as was the blind man miraculouſly reſtored to ſight (though borne blind) by Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.34. ond as it's noted of <hi>Julian,</hi> that infamous Revolt, not onely by feare and fraud, but even by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and preferments, he laboured to draw Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to blaſpheme, and to abjure the <hi>Galilean</hi> (as that miſcreant<note n="(r)" place="margin">Chriſtum ſubirdè Galilae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um [per igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniam] voci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavit, &amp; ſepre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> centra eundem libros blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos evomuit. <hi>Ignatius. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netus, in vitâ ejus.</hi>
                     </note> ſcoffingly called Chriſt) and to joyne with him in the worſhip of Idols.</item>
                  <item>3. To theſe may be added violent perſecution of the Profeſſors of the Chriſtian Truth, for Truths ſake, to the utmoſt of power, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.40. They [ſought] to kill Chriſt himſelfe who told them the truth, which he had heard of God; and <hi>John</hi> 5.16. it's ſaid, that the <hi>Jewes perſecuted Jeſus;</hi> yea, and after his crucifixion, made uſe of all manner of inſtruments, whom they thought likely to be brought over to their party, ſome devout, and honourable women (abuſing the weakneſſe of the ſexe to ſtrengthen their owne violence) and the chief men of a City, to raiſe perſecution againſt <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> for preaching Chriſt Jeſus unto the people at <hi>Antioch.</hi> 13.50.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now, in thoſe that are brought nearer unto Chriſt, there goeth with this ſin, a willfull deſertion of the truth, and Apoſtacy from it; 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. <hi>They turne back from the holy Commandement delivered unto them.</hi> But, this point being very tender, it muſt accordingly be handled with caution and warineſſe; and therefore you muſt here remember that ancient diſtinction, betwixt <hi>lapſus,</hi> and <hi>prolapſio,</hi> particular falls, and falling away: A ſpirituall man may be <hi>overtaken in a fault,</hi> Gal. 6.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by a ſlip with his foot (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) yea, very grievcus falls. We read of Gods
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38129:7"/>owne dear ſervants, who yet have recovered their ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Church of God; even <hi>a juſt man may fall ſeven times a day,</hi> that is, often in the<note n="(f)" place="margin">John 9.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, St. <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi>
               </note> day of his life-time (whether ye underſtand that fall of ſin, as ſome, or by ſin into affliction, as others expound it) yet he ſtill keeps the name of a juſt man, for that he riſeth againe, <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.16. <hi>Though he fall,</hi> ſaith the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, he ſhall not utterly be caſt downe, for the Lord uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him with his hand,</hi> Pſal. 37.24. Corruption even in the moſt mortified Saints, ſticks like to the ſpriggs of <hi>Ivy</hi> in an old wall, which though it be often lopped, yet it will be ſprouting againe forth, and hardly at all removed, or univerſally eradicated till the old wall it ſelfe be pulled down; ſin that<note n="(t)" place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> body of death will not, as a <hi>Jebuſite</hi> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> quite out of our coaſts, till the death of the body, and by the occaſion of ſins inhabitation, variety of temptations, from the world, from the fleſh, and from the devil, like the ſons of <hi>Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viah</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> prove<note n="(w)" place="margin">2 Sam. 3.39.</note> too hard for the beſt men, oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, in many particulars: That of <hi>Peter</hi> is almoſt peerleſſe, ſo againſt his knowledge and conſcience, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrably denying the knowledge of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. And the like read we of ſundry in the Primitive Church drawn, through fear, to deny the truth, and to worſhip Idols; concerning many of whom, the Fathers of the Church, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> concluded, that they were not to be denyed penance, or pardon, their very [<note n="(x)" place="margin">Neh. 1.11.</note> deſire] to be reſtored to the Church, teſtifying, that there falls were of infirmity, not of malice; wherefore, partiall declinations, whether in judgement, as thoſe effaſcina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Galatians</hi> declined, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. Or in zeal, and affection, as the Angel of the Church in <hi>Epheſus, Re.</hi> 2.4. or in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, wherein all of u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> com ſhort ſomtimes, either in the matter, or in the manner, or in the meaſure of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance; yea often inordinate acts, like ſprigs, or ſuckers under the choyceſt graff, break forth; theſe partiall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, I ſay, muſt be diſtinguiſhed from this Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38129:8"/>which we call whole, it being as<note n="(y)" place="margin">Jun. <hi>in</hi> Paral.</note> 
               <hi>Junius</hi> hath deſcribed it, <hi>Totius, ex toto, in totum defectio,</hi> a defection of the whole man, inward and outward, in judgment, conſcience, will, memory, affections, from all Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, and gracious goodneſſe, to all impiety, joyned with an obſtinate full reſolution never to embrace the ſame, or any part thereof againe.</p>
            <p>Theſe are their Facts.</p>
            <p>The Motive thereto, which ſpecially gives the form, ſpecifically framing it as it were to its proper nature, is Malice, obſtinate ſpight, deſtinate hatred, wherein they are carried againſt the Goſpel, &amp; all thoſe that embrace and profeſs it, treading under foot (even as<note n="(z)" place="margin">Mat. 7.6.</note> ſwine doe <hi>Margarites,</hi> and precious pearls) the Son of God, counting the blood of the Covenant, wherewith they were ſanctified, an unholy thing, doing deſpite unto the ſpirit of grace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29. that made<note n="a" place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de Temp. Ser. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 59. Vide <hi>P. Lombard.</hi> 2. ſ. Diſt. 43. lit. <hi>A. B. C. D.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it thus, <hi>Cum poſt agnitionem Dei per gratiam Domini noſtri Jeſu Chriſti, quiſquam oppugnat fraternitatem, &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus ipſam gratiam, quâ reconciliatus eſt Deo, invidentiae facibus agitatur:</hi> When grace, for pure grace ſake, is maliciouſly reſiſted, ſo that the grace of the ſpirit is the very ground of this whole pertinacious ſpight againſt the Spirit, the<note n="b" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>God of all ſanctifying and ſaving grace.</hi> And this is the reaſon S. <hi>Peter</hi> thus ſinned not, becauſe not ſpight, but feare prevailed with him; That hath alſo made it queſtionable, whether<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij Diſputat. ad 10. c. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Judas</hi> ſinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt, in betraying his Maſter, becauſe his fact ſeems not to have iſſued ſo much out of malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Saviours perſon or doctrine, but from his covetouſneſſe, and love of<note n="d" place="margin">Joh. 12.6.</note> the money-bag, which the Apoſtle calleth the<note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>root of all evill.</hi> That made it diſputable alſo, whether <hi>Demas</hi> his forſaking the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, be cenſurable of this ſin, for that not hatred of <hi>Pauls</hi> perſon, but love of the<note n="f" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>preſent world</hi> withdrew him: Yea, as we ſay not every<note n="g" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.14.</note> love of Gods children is a token of our tranſlating from death to life, unleſſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38129:8"/>they be loved, <hi>eo Nomine,</hi> becauſe they are gracious; ſo not every hatred, or perſecution, no not malicious of Gods children is to be ſo cenſured, except grace be that that mens malice is carried againſt, as it was in wicked <hi>Cain,</hi> againſt his righteous brother <hi>Abel,</hi> 1 John 3.12. It is a generall backſliding from the whole truth of the Goſpel acknowledged, and a malicious oppugning of the ſame, and that by all imaginable wicked meanes whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And thus far alſo of the Concomitants of this ſin unto death.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, and laſtly come to be obſerved the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequents, or dangerous effects of the ſame ſin.</p>
            <p>And theſe are,
<list>
                  <item>1. Obſtinate, and finall impenitency; obſtinacy is, <hi>Induratae mentis in malitiâ pertinacia,</hi> as<note n="h" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pet. Lomb.</hi> nbi ſupra.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter Lombard</hi> deſcribes it, a ſtubborn froward perſiſting of an hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned heart, in willfull malice, by which a man becomes, and is made impenitent, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4.6. It's impoſſible, not difficult onely, as ſome mince the matter) ſaith the Apoſtle, that ſuch enlightned Apoſtates ſhould be renewed againe unto repentance; and this too, not through defect in Gods mercy, which is as himſelfe it,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 145.9.</note> boundleſſe, infinite, incomprehenſible, but through the juſt judgment of God upon contempt of ſuch grace offered to them, giving them up unto a<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 1.28.</note> 
                     <hi>reprobate mind,</hi> and unto<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 2.5. Exod. 7.13. Rom. 9.</note> hardneſſe of heart, and to ſuch a ſtate as they cannot repent, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. ſometimes, perhaps, ſome of them com to a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to ſom after thought-taking, when they ſtruggle with the wrath of God on their guilty black conſcience, and wiſh as <hi>Judas,</hi> that their ſins had never been committed, only through horror under the apprehenſion of the everlaſting vengeance of God that awaites them; but never to a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or a change of their minds; ſo that impenitency finall is one Conſequent of this dreadfull and deadly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</item>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:38129:9"/>
                  <item>2. Peerleſſe vitioſity in heart and manners; ſuch men thus totally fallen, and finally rendred impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, become in all vitiouſneſſe far<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 12.44, 45.</note> more vile then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they were before their calling, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20. their latter end is worſe with them, than their beginning: and it hath been found moſt true in all experience, that none ever have proved more ſwiniſh to wallow in the mire of all<note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1.</note> 
                     <hi>pollutions of fleſh and ſpirit,</hi> then have vile Apoſtates; nor ever any more inſatiable <hi>Horſleaches,</hi> to ſuck out the blood of the ſaints of God, than ſuch who have metamorphized their firſt Chriſtian profeſſion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an after degenerous and Antichriſtian perſecution.<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Vid.</hi> Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan. de Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mangis.</note> 
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince it became Antichriſtian hath proved more vile, then when it was at firſt Paganiſh.</item>
                  <item>3. Irremiſſibility, and finall impardonableneſſe: <hi>Wherefore I ſay unto you,</hi> ſaith our Saviour,(<note n="m" place="margin">Conf. Mar. 3.29. &amp; Luc. 12.10.</note>) Mat. 12.31, 32. <hi>all manner of Sin and Blaſphemy ſhall be forgiven unto men: But the Blaſphemy againſt the</hi> Holy Ghoſt <hi>ſhall not be forgiven unto men. And whoſoever ſpeaketh a word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Son of man, it ſhall be forgiven him: But whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſpeaketh againſt the</hi> Holy Ghoſt, <hi>it ſhall not be forgiven him, neither in this World, nor in the World to come.</hi> Now that all ſin, and all manner of other ſins (but this one) have been forgiven unto men, namely unto men capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of forgivenes, ſuch are onely the elect of God, and the believing penitents (for its a knowne Maxime in Orthodox Divinity, <hi>Nulla peccata remittuntur reprobis,</hi> No ſins are pardoned to the reprobate, and the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately impenitent) This, I ſaid, I ſhall manifeſt unto you; for as in the brighteſt ſerenity of the Moon, ſo the Church (which <hi>Solomon</hi> reſembleth unto the Moon, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.10.) hath when it is at the cleareſt, in its militant condition here below, ſome blots, and ſpots that doe blemiſh often the pulchritude and beauty of it: inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that we read of ſome great Saints ſinning, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, even groſſe and enormous ſins, ſo<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 9.22.</note> 
                     <hi>Noah</hi> fell by drunkenneſſe,<note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 19.33.35.</note> 
                     <hi>Lot</hi> by inceſt with his owne daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38129:9"/>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">2 Sam. 11.4.</note> 
                     <hi>David</hi> by adultery,<note n="q" place="margin">1 Kings 11.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Solomon</hi> by idolatry,<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 26.74.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter</hi> by perjury, even all the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mar. 4.40.</note> Apoſtles by partiall infidelity, yet theſe found place for repentance, and upon that, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and pardon; yee ſhall read in the<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 1.</note> Genealogy of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, a catalogue of perſons<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 30.39.</note> ſpeck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led like <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſheep (watered in the gutters of <hi>Laban</hi>) into variety of ſins, ſome <hi>Jewes,</hi> ſome <hi>Gentiles,</hi> all, or moſt of them <hi>tainted;</hi> for this end, among others, record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that miſerable ſinners might know that Chriſt came into the world as the univerſal Phyſitian, both able and willing to<note n="w" place="margin">Pſa. 41.4.</note> heal every diſeaſed ſoul, yea ſuch a Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an as comes home often unſent for, going<note n="x" place="margin">Acts 10.38.</note> about doing good, and curing all<note n="y" place="margin">Luke 4.40.</note> kind and<note n="z" place="margin">Mat. 4.23.</note> manner of diſeaſes; he is that<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 10.33.</note> pittying <hi>Samaritan,</hi> who cannot paſſe by a<note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 18.14.</note> wounded ſpirit without pouring in the oyle of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, had ſuch but firſt a<note n="c" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.13.</note> ſight, and<note n="d" place="margin">1 Kin. 8.33.</note> ſenſe of their own wounds; yea, he was ſuch a Phyſitian, who for to ſave the lives, and to redeem the ſouls of penitent patients from death, moſt chearfully<note n="e" place="margin">Jo. 10.17, 18.</note> laid down his owne life,<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 23.34.</note> praying for them that<note n="g" place="margin">Matth. 27, 29, 30, 31.</note> mocked,<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 27.39. 1 Pet. 2.13.</note> reviled,<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 27.35. Phil. 2.8.</note> crucified,<note n="k" place="margin">Acts 2.23. &amp; 3.15. &amp; 7.52.</note> murdered him; yea here in this Scripture (but now na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to you) that the blaſphemy of the Son of man, that is, of Chriſt himſelf, who veiling for a time the glorious ſplendor of his Divinity, by the fleſh of his obſure Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, was ſuppoſed by the ignorant <hi>Jewes,</hi> to be but a<note n="l" place="margin">Phil. 2.7, 8.</note> mean man, though he were, at the ſame time, the<note n="m" place="margin">Pſa. 24.7, 8.</note> King of glory, and ſo they filled their mouths with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of him, charging him with whole volleyes of the higheſt blaſphemies, ſtiling him<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 27.63.</note> deceiver,<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 11.19.</note> glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, contemptuouſly,<note n="p" place="margin">Jo. 8.48.</note> 
                     <hi>Samaritan,</hi>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 12.24. Joh. 9.29.</note> this fellow, a<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 11.19.</note> friend of <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>ſinners,</hi> one who had a<note n="ſ" place="margin">Jo. 8.52.</note> devil, and what miracles he did, he wrought them by the<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 12.24.</note> 
                     <hi>Prince of devils;</hi> O horrid! lo yet and ſee, even this blaſphemy, ſo high, ſo notorious, ſo diſhonourable, is pardonable to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting blaſphemers; but the blaſphemy of the Holy Ghoſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>[mipeſcha rab]</hi> that great offence, with an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſo called by King <hi>David,</hi> who prayed ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38129:10"/>to be preſerved from it, <hi>Pſ</hi> 19.13. This blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (God in his juſtice denying the grace of repentance to it) this is utterly irremiſſible, everlaſtingly unpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, even unto all eternity; wherefore, it is added, <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this world, nor in the world to com,</hi> not, in this world, becauſe, ſay ſom, blaſphemy coming (at leaſt during the Jewiſh adminiſtration) under the cognizance, &amp; power of the Magiſtrate, it was no way, by no means capable of any reprieve at all, but the ſoul<note n="n" place="margin">Lev. 24.16. Vid. <hi>Simon majolum,</hi> lib. De perfidiâ Indaeor. p 73. &amp; 241, 242, <hi>&amp;c. Blaſphemia, &amp; ſpiritus Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemiae diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt: ſpisitus blaſphemiae ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirat ad odium Dei<hi rend="sup">s</hi> ſicùt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſanctus ad dei amorem; Blaſphemia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittetur, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus a Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miae non.</hi> Joh. Altenſtaig in ſer. Theolog. in voc. Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemia, p. 102, 103. v.d. Dieterie: Dn: 19. poſt Trin. p. 747, 748. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> ſo ſinning muſt be cut off without mercy, from Gods people, and be ſtoned to death; or more generally thus, not in this world by any promiſe, or aſſurance of it at all from heaven, or the word of God, the patent of penitents (but not of ſuch final impenitents) for pardon: nor in the <hi>world</hi> to come, underſtand it thus, not as ſuppoſing, by that expreſſion, any hopes remaining (after death) to any other kind of ſinners, whoſe life expired, as it was lead in a courſe of preſumptuous impenitency (as the great Patrons of <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory</hi> would perſwade their ignorant &amp; beſotted pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelites) but this is only a diſtribution, or diviſive ſpeech, intended not to ſignifie things divers, but to aggravate and to exagerate the ſame thing; and uſed it is, it may be, purpoſely to lay a ſtumbling-block in the way of the obſtinate, to reſtrain and to withhold them from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſo deſperately, and with an high hand againſt the Lord, ſo as therby they wilfully cut themſelves off from all preſent, future, or ſucceeding hopes of mercy to their graceles ſouls: In a word, the ſin againſt the father is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the redemption of the ſon; the ſin againſt the Son is pardoned through the application of his merit, by the Holy Ghoſt, but the ſin againſt the Spirit hath no remiſſion, becauſe there is no way of expiation, there being by God in judgment intercluded the way to the mean of mercy, which is repentance; ſuch men therfore (ſo ſining) ſhall the ſpirit himſelf<note n="w" place="margin">Jo. 16.8.</note> convince of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto confuſion; for ſaith the great Apoſtle, <hi>If we ſin wilfully after that we have received the knowledge of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38129:10"/>truth, there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſin,</hi> but a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſearful looking for of judgment, and fiery indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which ſhal devour the adverſaries, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26, 27. And for this cauſe is it, that this ſin is here ſtiled by S. <hi>John,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a ſin unto death, and that, not only becauſe in its own nature it deſerves the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon death, conſiſting in the ſeparation of the ſoul from the body, for this is the wages of every ſin, <hi>Rm</hi> 6.23. but becauſe it being the will of God to ſhut up under final impenitency the men ſo ſining, it merits, and ſo ſhall infallibly incur not that only which is called the<note n="x" place="margin">Ioſb. 23.14.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way of all the earth in the temporal death, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſentence and ſenſe of the<note n="y" place="margin">Rev. 2.11.</note> ſecond death; which ſecond or eternal death conſiſteth in the<note n="z" place="margin">Mat. 25.41, 46. 2 Theſſ. 2.9.</note> everlaſting ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of both ſoul and body, from Gods gracious and glorious preſence (which is the puniſhment alſo) &amp; withall (which is the puniſhment of ſenſe) the plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of both into inexpreſſible torments with the devil, his accurſed Angels, and all other damned blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſpirits, even for ever and ever.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſin, for the nature of it very hainous, and for the danger of it (as ye have it thus declared to you) moſt diſmal and full of horror.</p>
            <p>A word or two further of the ſtile or titles given here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto in holy writ, which was the ſecond general Head of my diviſion propoſed; of which ſuccinctly, that (withall conſidering the great affairs enſuing) I may haſten to my Application, in which indeed conſiſteth all the marrow, and<note n="*" place="margin">Pſa. 36.8.</note> ſatnes, even the very life and vigor of every ſolid Sermon, and divine diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The ſtile or title given to it by our Saviour, is, as ye heard but now, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.31. <hi>The Blaſphemy of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> that is, the endeavouring to diſhonour the holy Ghoſt, it is a Greek word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as it were hurting (if I may dare ſo to expreſſe it) the fame, and blurring the glory of the holy Spirit? But why of the holy Ghoſt? and not of the Father, or of the Son?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38129:11"/>is not the whole Trinity one Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24. each per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is God, equal in majeſty &amp; glory, and <hi>God is a Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Queſt."/>
               <hi>There is an inquiry made, Whether, indeed, a man may not ſo ſin againſt one perſon of the Trinity, that in that Fact, he ſins not againſt the whole Trinity?</hi> To which the reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, That virtually, and in the iſſue, the ſin reacheth to the whole three perſons; however, <hi>intentionally,</hi> one alone be ſtricken at. <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alex. Hal.</hi> f. 704. in fronte</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſw."/>
               <hi>Alexander</hi>* <hi>Halenſis</hi> (the <hi>Patriarch</hi> of the School Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines)<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Durand.</hi> l. 2. diſt. 13. qu. 1. in ſenti.</note> 
               <hi>Durandus,</hi> and other of that rank, conceive, that there are divine properties, in reſpect of their exerciſe, appropriated to the ſeveral perſons, as <hi>power</hi> to the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wiſedome</hi> to the <hi>Son,</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe</hi> to the <hi>holy Ghoſt;</hi> ſo that a ſin of <hi>weaknes</hi> or <hi>infirmity,</hi> is committed againſt the <hi>Father,</hi> that is, againſt the <hi>power</hi> of God; a ſin of <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> is committed againſt the <hi>Son,</hi> that is, againſt the <hi>wiſedome</hi> of God; a ſin of <hi>wickedneſſe, malice,</hi> or <hi>hatred,</hi> is committed againſt the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> that is, againſt the <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God.</hi> But waving theſe curioſities, ſpun upon the wheel of mens quaint apprehenſions, however in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (thus applyed) not wholy impertinent, this blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy is ſo called, not becauſe it's intended ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the<note n="c" place="margin">S. Auguſt. <hi>l. 1. c. 11.</hi> De. Trin.</note> perſon of the holy Ghoſt, the third perſon in the bleſſed Trinity, as againſt the proper<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin.</hi> q. 7. Catech.</note> operation and efficacious work of the holy Ghoſt. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gerard: <hi>quâ ſupra.</hi> ſ. 109.</note> 
               <hi>Gerard</hi> (a moſt learned <hi>Lutheran</hi> Divine) thus gives his expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this ſtile; <hi>It's ſo ſtiled,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>partly in regard of the miniſtration of the ſpirit, which is the glorious Goſpel, he applying and ſweetly diffuſing into the hearts of all contrite and diſconſolate Chriſtians, the comforts and promiſes of grace therein contained, through the blood of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.8. <hi>in reſpect whereof he is likewiſe ſtiled, The Comforter,</hi> John 15.26. <hi>And partly alſo in regard of his office, which is illumination, and enlightning of the minds of his elect,</hi> Eph. 1.18. <hi>in reſpect whereof he is in his operation compared to fire,</hi> Mat. 3.11. <hi>as well for light, as for heat, and therefore the ſhunning of that light is called, the Quenching of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:38129:11"/>1 Theſſ. 5.19. <hi>And laſtly, in regard of his gracious te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, and witneſſe, teſtifying and witneſſing to the ſpirit of believers, That they are the ſons of God,</hi> Rom. 8.16. To which alſo may be added his directive manuduction, leading the elect into all neceſſary fundamental truth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.13. And ſo much, in ſum, for the reaſon of this ſtile given hereto in holy writ.</p>
            <p>We may not, in the next place, omit to take notice of the Epithite that is given to it in another Scripture, at which I gave a glance but now; it is in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 19.13. where it is called by the Prophet, <hi>The [Great] Offence,</hi> ſo indeed by an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, even without peer, <hi>Non eſt majus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lictam,</hi> amongſt all ſins that Caſt-away's fall into, as there are many foul and erroneous, none ſo great as this: Truth is, whatever a man can think of to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate a ſin to the height of haynous, in this all concur: Their Facts imply<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> 
               <hi>Contempt of the Son of God, prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the blood of the Covenant,</hi> contumely to the holy Ghoſt; beſides all this, Fouleſt ingratitude to that God who offered ſo great grace to their ſouls, declared by their blaſpheming the truth, oppugning the ſpeaking of it, ſo glorious to God, ſo healthful to men; Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances yet make it fouler, the Motive eſpecially, for <hi>That it iſſues out of malice, and deſtinate ſpight againſt the majeſty of God.</hi> No marvaile then was it, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our taught it to be unpardonable, that is, not as ſome interpret, hardly pardonable, but utterly uncapable of pardon, through a juſt Ordinance of God, ſhutting up the fountaine of his mercy againſt the ſouls of ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious and godleſſe miſcreants: and hither, to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, may well be applyed that paſſage in <hi>Solomons</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs, <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.18. where he ſaith, that <hi>whoſo walketh uprightly, ſhall be ſaved, but he that is perverſe in his wayes, ſhall fall at once;</hi> the emphaſis lyeth in that clauſe <hi>[at once] Semel dicitur cadere qui irreparabiliter cadit,</hi> as<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alex. Hal.</hi> part. 4. qu. 12. mem. 5. art. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Halenſis</hi> expounds it, he is ſaid to fall <hi>at once,</hi> who fals beyond hope of recovery, irreparably, and ſo that texs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38129:12"/>is meant, not of a common ſlipping aſide, but of a final back ſliding <hi>(Perverſis graditur viis, id eſt, perfectè verſis)</hi> which happeneth in final impenitency: and this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Solomon</hi> ſeems to me to be equivalent to what our Saviour pronounced on thoſe blaſphemous <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees,</hi> Joh. 9.41. when he declared that their <hi>ſin [remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed]</hi> that whereas a ſin of ignorance (though in it ſelfe enormous) might be capable of pardon, which is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from many Scriptures and examples, as <hi>Num.</hi> 15.27, 28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.7. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. Yet, their preſumptuous blaſpheming againſt profeſſed knowledge, clear ſight, and evidence of truth, this their ſin was not a ſlight or a tranſient act, and ſo to be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over as ſometimes God did <hi>Jacob,</hi> without being <hi>[ſeen]</hi> or obſerved for puniſhment, <hi>Num.</hi> 23.21. but it is a ſin <hi>[remaining]</hi> as it were written with the<note n="h" place="margin">Ier. 17.1.</note> 
               <hi>poynt of a diamond;</hi> the Actors of it being, as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>alwayes</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſ. 109.15.</note> 
               <hi>before the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Legatur</hi> Beza ad 1 Io. 5.16. <hi>fusè explican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem naturam peccati iſtius:</hi> Confer: B<hi rend="sup">p</hi>. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> in his Sum of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion p. 151, 152. Edit. 1648.</note> 
               <hi>that he might have both them and their ſin in his ſight, and remembrance, never to blot out, or to remit it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, to recapitulate the ſum of all, the Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt is no leſſe then, <hi>A willfull mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and obſtinate denying of the foundation, renounſing Chriſt Jeſus as the Mediator and Redeemer of the world; It is a to tall Apoſtacy from the Faith, when the whole man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volteth from the whole Chriſtian Religion, wholly, with an obſtinate reſolution never to returne to it any more; neither is it poſſible for him that is guilty thereof to mourn, and lament for his ſins; his ſtubborn and reprobate heart is not ſo tender, but being paſt all ſorrow and feeling, rather</hi> (as<note n="k" place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Jo. Down</hi> in Tract: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Baxter.</hi>
               </note> one farther adds to expreſſe the meaſure of it) <hi>rejoyceth and boaſteth in his deſperate and malicious obſtinacy.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Soli filij irae iram non ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, ſed laetan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; exult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant in rebus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſimio. <hi>Ber. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 52.1. Iam. 4.16. Deut. 29.19.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſin, for nature moſt hainous, for the iſſue moſt dangerous, dreadful, formidable; in the mention whereof, me-thinks the powers of mens ſouls cannot but be ſhaken, their thoughts trouble them, and as<note n="m" place="margin">Dan. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Belſhazzar's</hi> at the fight of the hand-writing upon the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38129:12"/>wall (whileſt he ſat quaffing in the veſſels of the ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary) the joynts of their loynes be looſed, and their knees ſmite one againſt another.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ʋſe I."/> Come we now, in order, to the Uſe and Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Beloved Chriſtians, according to the grievous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this ſin, ſo let all thoſe uſe the meditation of it, whom God hath called to the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, that by meditation of the foulneſſe of it,<note n="n" place="margin">Pſa 147.20. 1 Cor. 1.21.</note> their care may be encreaſed to preſerve themſelves from it: It's a great favour God hath granted us, that <hi>unto us he hath vouch ſafed, in the means, the knowledge of himſelfe, in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> he hath not dealt ſo with many Nations more, that herewithall he hath daigned alſo to<note n="o" place="margin">Eph. 1.18.</note> enlighten the eyes of our underſtanding, to know the<note n="p" place="margin">Eph. 3.3, 4. 1 Tim. 3.16.</note> myſtery of Godlineſſe, he hath not dealt ſo with many Children of the Church; many (the more is the pity) live ſtil in groſſe ignorance of neceſſarieſt Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: To ſome of us yet more, that he hath given us<note n="q" place="margin">Phil. 1.29. Eph. 2.8.</note> faith to believe it; woe is me! that there ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us many of ripe underſtanding, that yet dare queſtion the truth of the Goſpel: yea, to ſome yet more, he hath granted<note n="r" place="margin">Phil. 1.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſenſe of the comfort, of the<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.3. 2. Cor. 2.14.</note> ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and perhaps alſo of the<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> power thereof to reform us:<note n="u" place="margin">Ioſh. 23.11. Heb. 3.12. Preſervatives againſt the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</note> Take heed Brethren, that ſo great favour of God be not fruſtrate by our <hi>unthankefull</hi> Apoſtacy.</p>
            <p>Among many <hi>Preſervatives</hi> that might happily be ſet down, to keep men from Apoſtacy, and from this great ſin, give me leave to offer to your conſiderations, theſe following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Labour by all means to faſten on your hearts the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>love of that ſaving truth wherein you have been enlightned;</hi> ſtrong deluſion is ſent upon men that received not the love of the truth; there is a diſeaſe of latter times called the <hi>Rickets,</hi> when Children rather ſwel then grow in the upper parts, and find a luxation of members, and a debility downwards; ſo it's become now likewiſe a diſeaſe in the ſpiritual part of men, they ſwel like the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38129:13"/>ancient <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> with knowledge in the brain, with<note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 8.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] 1 Cor. 8.1.</note> puffing ſpeculations ſwiming in the head, but have little affection of what they ſo apprehend in pure notion: but my brethren, when all is done, it is not the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing head, but it is the underſtanding heart, that availeth to ſolid happines: The red<note n="y" place="margin">Rev. 12.4.</note> Dragon in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> is obſerved to have drawn the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> part of thoſe who were as ſtars for light, with him unto the earth; wherefore, the moſt experienced Caſuiſts have reſolved, That Gods School is more of holy ſanctified affection, then of meer notional, or floating ſpeculation: and ſo it hath been found true in all Hiſtories of the Church, that unſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied wits abounding with variety of learning, as <hi>Arrius, Porphyrie,</hi> and other like; Satan hath made uſe of to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and to deprave the truth of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Carefully preſerve Conſcience from known diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> it's dangerous to ſlight the ſtrokes thereof, when it<note n="z" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.5.</note> ſmites thee for the act, and perpetration of that, whereof thy conſcience is<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 8.9.</note> convinced it is ſin; when men ſtop their<note n="b" place="margin">Pſa. 58.5.</note> ears againſt the directions of that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Monitor which God (as his principal Vice-gerent in the ſoul) hath placed in every boſome, they are in great peril of a down-fal; yea, that's the means, at <hi>length</hi> to make it filent, and ſo by degrees in the iſſue, through<note n="c" place="margin">Ex conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine peccandi Dei metus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, &amp; contemptus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutitur. <hi>S. Aug.</hi>
               </note> cuſtom,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph. 4.19.</hi> Primò decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes â medio capimur, capti occaecamur, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caecati obdureſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus, obdura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti deſperamus: <hi>Caſ:</hi> in <hi>Eth:</hi>
               </note> ſenſles, which in ſenſibility is the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſtate of the conſcience, <hi>Scio longius â ſalute abſiſtere membrum quod obſtupuit, &amp; aegrum ſeſe non ſentientem, peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culoſius laborare,</hi> as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaks, A ſtupified member is hardly curable but by corraſives, if at all by them; &amp; there is by far more hope of the curation of one ſick (though very far gone) who is ſenfible of his malady, then of him, who before he doth, or will ſee his diſeaſe, is ſwallowed up in a miſcarriage: That one example is memorable of <hi>Hymineus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> who having not joyned to their Science<note n="*" place="margin">Conſcientia mala ſine deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratione non eſt. <hi>S. Aug. praef. ſuper. Pſal. 31.</hi>
               </note> Conſcience, having put away the one, they loſt the ſoundnes of the other, and made ſhipwrack of their Faith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19.20.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:38129:13"/>
            <p n="3">3. Cheriſh by all means the ſweet motions of grace, and of the ſpirit of God: 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 5.19. O take heed, vex him not. <hi>Iſa:</hi> 63.10. grieve him not: <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.30. rather let thine ears hear that word behind thee, ſaying: <hi>This is the way, walk ye in it, Iſa.</hi> 30.21: it may be there are many of you here preſent, who now hear this no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe this day, in the Miniſtry of this very word now ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into your ears. Be afraid how ye neglect to be<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 16.13. Pſal. 143.10.</note> lead and guided by this good ſpirit of God ſpeaking to you in that very<note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 59.21.</note> word which himſelf hath<note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.</note> inſpired; its ſaid to recount the caſe of many men in this behalf, that throw off ſuch motions with diſregard, and deem them (through the<note n="d" place="margin">Jer. 17.9.</note> deceitfulnes of their hearts, the<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 3.13.</note> deceitfulnes of ſin, &amp; the cunning inſinuations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than) but fits of melancholy ariſing from the naturall complexion of the body, or ſome ſudden qualnes of conſcience that do ſurpriſe them. Beloved Brethren, I beſeech you conſider that when God offers ſuch grace, he offers himſelf to you as to Children, if ye be<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8.14.</note> led by the Spirit of God, and that not only in point of<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 25.12. Mic. 6.8.</note> direction. and of<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa 30.21.</note> inſtigations (unto which ſteps is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as if I had time might be demonſtrated for an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate man to aſcend) but chiefly in reſpect of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valence, ſo that by way of eminence, and ruling pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominancy, you are led by him, then are you the ſons of God in good earneſt: 4. Prudently notice,<note place="margin">Rom: 8.14</note> and with all ſpirituall<note n="i" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> circumſpection, obſerve thy declinings, and abatements of thy meaſures of grace, and how thy devotion, or zeal (which ſhould not like <hi>Ioſhuas</hi> ſun ſtand<note n="k" place="margin">Joſh. 10.13.</note> ſtill, but like <hi>Davids</hi> ſun rather rejoyce as a Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 19.5. 2 King. 20.10.</note> to run a race onwards in its courſe) how it doth<note n="m" place="margin">Iſa. 38.8.</note> go back like <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> ſun, in its degrees; and never leave the ſtrick reſt uſe of the moſt conſcientious means, till thou haſt recovered thy antient meaſures: <hi>Rev:</hi> 24.5. Yea I will be bold to ſay thus much further: No Chriſtian can poſſibly have any ſolid aſſurance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on firm grounds, of any truth of ſaving grace begun
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:38129:14"/>in the heart, who is not carefull to cheriſh, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it by thoſe means which God hath ſanctified to that end, and therefore he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and Teachers for the work of the Miniſtery, not only to gather the Saints together, by<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.5, 6, 7.</note> planting of true Doctrine in the Church; but alſo to<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.10.</note> confirm, ſtrengthen, ſettle, ſtabliſh, yea to [perfect] the ſame Saints, under the uſe of the ſame means of their firſt calling; ſee to this purpoſe: <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.11.12, 13. to the ſame effect is it, thas we read <hi>Cant:</hi> 3.1, 1, 3, 4 Where we may eaſilie diſcover the behaviour of the Spouſe, or Church of Chriſt languiſhing under the abſence, or the withdrawing of her Miſticall Husband Jeſus Chriſt: what doth ſhe do? Why, make diligent enquiry, and ſtrict ſearch after him, leaving no wayes or means un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attempted, and is reſtles till ſhe had again found him whom her ſoul loved: in thoſe wayes wherein (in all probability) ſhe had left him, in thoſe when ſhe ſought him. Yet there ſeeking ſhe found him not: <hi>By night in my bed I ſought him whom my ſoul loveth, I ſought him, but I found him not;</hi> in her Bed the plaſe of eaſe, and reſt, (ſhe means when ſhe had too<note n="*" place="margin">Indulgendum ſomno eſt, ut corpus reparet, non reſolvat, &amp; vires revocet, non enervet. <hi>Chryſolog. ſer. 24.</hi> Non ſit ſepultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſuffocati, ſed requies laſſi. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
               </note> much indulged thereto) lulling her ſelf a ſleep in a ſupine regardleſnes, and ſecurity, there ſhe found him not: Chriſt hath no inward ſenſible com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with a reſty, unactive, lazy ſoul, for Chriſtians muſt not be Cretians, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 1.12.</note> ſlow bellies: Well, what courſe doth ſhe take next, I will riſe now (ſaith ſhe) leave my drowzy temper, and being riſen, I will go about the City in the ſtreets, and in the broad wayes, I will ſeek him whom my ſoul loveth, that is, among thoſe who ſtand<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 20.6.</note> idle, &amp; loitring in the Market places, unemployed in their own, though<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.15.</note> buſie bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies enough, perhaps about the doings of others, or elſ ſuch as following the guize of wavering times, meteo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing as it were, and unreſolved, or indifferent in the matters of Religion, run on in a full career the ſmooth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:38129:14"/>broad wayes to what is dangerous, ſhe ſought him there, but ſhe miſſed of her aim, ſhe ſought him, but ſhe found him not: Wel, do but obſerve her in her carriage but a little farther, and then, but not till then, ſhe finds him. <hi>The watchmen that go about the City found me to whom I ſaid, Saw ye him whom my ſoul loveth?</hi> What are theſe<note n="*" place="margin">Ezek. 3.17. Heb. 13.19.</note> Watch men? but thoſe ſpiritual Paſtors, or Miniſters, whoſe office is to give warning, upon due, and ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able diſcovery, of the danger of the Souls enemies, as themſelves watching over them for good, even as thoſe who muſt give account in the day of judgment, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.17. Well, the text adds, <hi>It was but a little that I paſſed from them, but I found Him, whom my ſoul loveth;</hi> to imply, that whileſt ſhe ſought for Chriſt, where indeed He was to be found, namely, <hi>by the footſteps of the flocks, and by the ſhepherds tents:</hi> Cant: 1.8. there, if any where, among ſuch Inſtruments of conveying him in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrey unto her ſoul, He was to be heard of, and actually found; By the ſame Meſſengers who were firſt<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> ſent by God, with a Commiſſion to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of peace, &amp; to bring glad tydings of good things; even by the ſame (if not in individuall, yet in kinde) did, and doth the Church again recover the preſence, and with it the joy, and ſweetneſs thereof to her di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed ſpirits: to the like purpoſe alſo may we hither apply that gloſs which S. <hi>Bernard</hi> gives upon the with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drawing of <hi>Thomas</hi> from the company of the other Apoſtles unto whom the Lord Chriſt manifeſted Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf after his reſurrection, but not unto him being then<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 20.24.</note> away; <hi>Falleris Thomâ ſancte, falleris, ſi ab Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtolorum collegio ſegregatus invenire Chriſtum ſperas:</hi> O <hi>Thomas,</hi> thou art deceived, if thou hopeſt to find Chriſt ſevered from the congregation of the Apoſtles, and Saints of God; Wherefore is it, that the Apoſtle ſo zealouſly exhorts the Hebrews, <hi>Hebr:</hi> 10.25. not to forſake the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of themſelves together, as the manner of ſome is: and, that man after Gods own heart, ſee how reſtleſs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:38129:15"/>his ſoul is, till he could (after a forced abſence from thence) again viſit thoſe amiable tabernacles of the Lord of hoſts; mark, I beſeech you, what pathetick metaphors or ſimilitudes he borrows to illuſtrate, or expreſs his zealous anhelations, and gaſpings af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er God; the one of a woman under her <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (with whom there is <hi>pallor in ore, &amp; tremor in corde</hi>) her fits of longing, which if unſatisfied endanger ſwooning, yea often life it ſelf: <hi>Pſal:</hi> 84.2. <hi>My ſoul longeth, yea, even faint<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth for the cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts of the Lord: my heart and my fleſh crieth out for the living God.</hi> The other of the Hart braying after water, and readie even to ſink down dead before the bloodie purſuers; <hi>As the hart</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal 42.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>panteth after the water brooks, ſo panteth my ſoul after Thee, O God; My ſoul thirſteth for God for the living God; When ſhall I come, and appear before God?</hi> His meaning is, to declare the ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion he lately had, and now moſt fervently again deſired to renew with God, under the enjoyment of his reſtored, ſoul ſaving Ordinances, diſperſed in the Sanctuary: ſo that this may well be ſet down as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſervative againſt this dangerous downfall.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Take heed, how thou doeſt allow, or bear with thy ſelf in any preſumptuous ſin, yea though but in one ſingle particular: If thou willingly lye down un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power, dominion,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> reign of any one known ſin, whereof thy judgment and conſcience, upon clear evidence of Scripture is convinced that it is a ſin, thou canſt not promiſe thy ſelf an immunity, or freedom from the greateſt ſin: alas! what odds is it, in the iſſue, whether i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſhip ſink, or be ſplit in ſunder, it be by ſome inſenſible, ſecret leak, or by ſome violent blaſt that daſheth the ribs thereof againſt the rocks? or, if a bird be taken in the gin, whether by one claw, or by the whole body, ſo it come into the hands of the fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, as a prey? and, indeed, the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.26. uſeth the very ſame metaphor of men held captive at the will of the Devill, they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, taken
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:38129:15"/>alive, even as a Bird is trapped in a ſnare, and at the pleaſure of the Devil to tempt, or to torment him: one mire may defile a ſow, one ſword deſtroy a man, one diſeaſe, as well as a thouſand bring him to his grave, even one ſin unrepented of, endanger the ſoul to Hell. Now, for the proof of this, conſult I beſeech you, with that clear Text, Pſal: 19.13. <hi>Keep back thy ſervant alſo from preſumptuous ſins, let them not have [dominion] over me: then ſhall I be upright, and I ſhall be innocent from the great tranſgreſſion:</hi> from this Scripture it is very clear that even <hi>David</hi> himſelf could not ſecure himſelf from this ſin, in caſe he had born with himſelf under the <hi>[reigne]</hi> of particular preſumptions: Certainly, I dare ſay he was of his mind, a man as he, enlightned a Member of the Church, living under the dominion of any ſin, was endangered to the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which here he cals the great tranſgreſſion: When Conſcience once grows incenſible of ſin, as through [<note n="*" place="margin">Tanta eſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptela malae conſuetudinis, ut ab eâ igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi extinguan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur â naturâ dati, exoriantur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vitia contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria. <hi>Cic. li. 1. de Leg.</hi>
               </note> cuſtome] of evill every conſcience doth; what ſin, or degree of ſin can a man ſecure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from? <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.19. When a man is once paſt feeling, he gives himſelf to commit ſin with greedines, then follows oft in Gods Judgment, ſpiritual deſertion, God gives a man over to the ſwing of his own corrupt heart, and to the power of Sathan; and he muſt needs go (we ſay) whom the Devil drives: Wherefore dear Chriſtians, and Countrymen,<note n="*" place="margin">Heb 13.22.</note> ſuffer the word of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, and let the admonition be that of <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.19. <hi>Let every one that names the name of Chriſt depart from iniquity.</hi> The pure grace of the glorious Goſpel is no<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 6.1. Gal. 5.13.</note> warrant for any impure, ranting licentiouſnes: Tremble to bear with thy ſelf in any ſin againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, nor to let ſin reign in thy mortal body, leſt thou endanger thy ſelf to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſin, which is unto death.</p>
            <p>Beloved, its a great mercy of God to be born in the Church, and to enjoy the priviledges (though but out ward) of it, and yet this think of: The ſtate of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Church may prove worſe a great deal,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:38129:16"/>than the ſtate of Jews, and Pagans, that never yet gave entertainment to the Goſpel, though they have ſins enough to damn them, yet they are out of danger of this ſin unpardonable; therefore be exhorted, and the more alſo, for that its ſtrange to ſee the ſtrong<note n="a" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.11.</note> deluſion ſent upon many, that though they<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 29.19</note> bleſs themſelves in their wickednes, and add drunkenes to thirſt, yet ſeem to be out of danger of other groſſe ſins; whereas its demonſtrative from what hath been thus collected from this of <hi>David,</hi> that no man can promiſe himſelf a freedome from the fouleſt ſins, in whom any ſin reigns.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (for I haſten) let not that be forgotten of the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb:</hi> 6.1. who upon this very ground, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth ſaying, <hi>Let us go on unto perfection:</hi> compare 2 Pet: 3.18. <hi>For its impoſſible that if we fall away,</hi> (he means univerſally) <hi>we ſhould again be renewed unto a true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> he ſeems to take it for granted, that there is no mean between ſeeming ſufficiency, and certain Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: and this withall remember, that our growth will be expected, and accounted for, according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6, 7. Heb. 6.7.</note> watering, and thoſe means of grace which the Lord hath afforded us; it ſhall be charged more heavily upon the ſcore of <hi>Chorazin,</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> and <hi>Capernaum</hi> in the day of Judgment, than upon <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> yea or upon <hi>Sodome</hi> &amp; <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> though thoſe Cities were of moſt prodigious, and even<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 1.26, 27.</note> unnaturall abominations: the reaſon is, becauſe they had more means by preaching miracles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than the other had.</p>
            <p>To draw towards a concluſion: Beloved Chriſtians let every one now, upon theſe ſeverall intimations, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 77.6.</note> commune with his own heart, and let his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit make diligent ſearch, examine and<note n="b" place="margin">Lam. 3.40.</note> cry himſelf into what degrees of this ſin he hath grown, that as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake to that<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 8.22.</note> 
               <hi>Simon, If it be poſſible, his ſin may be forgiven him,</hi> whilſt every one endeavours to recover his firſt eſtate, and to do his firſt works. <hi>Rev:</hi> 2.4.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:38129:16"/>
            <p>We have been many of us brought paſt the antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of this ſin; the Lord hath declared unto us the truth of the Goſpel, and oh, how pretious, not only in regard of the rarity, but of the valuation and eſteem, as the word of God in the dayes of<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Samuel,</hi> was the light thereof, when it firſt brake out in theſe parts? I doubt not but with many of us, illumination hath been ſo clear, that we have been convinced, and ſome kind of profeſſion moſt of us have made of the Goſpel. And yet alas! lamentable is the ſtate of many<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 7.51.</note> reſiſting the truth, and too much<note n="b" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25</note> oppoſing againſt it, whereby the courſe of the Goſpel is not a little ſtopped, at leſt in the purity thereof: Hereunto may be added<note n="c" place="margin">Joh. 9 28. 1 Cor. 5.11. 1 Cor. 6.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, rayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>dicitur, â</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as it were to excoriate, and skin a man: or, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtathius:</hi> A word wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like a ſharp ſpear; by <hi>David</hi> the wicked tongue is compared to a ſharp razor, Pſal. 52.2.</note> railings, and blaſphemies of the multitude; How many ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals raiſed, I ſay not of the perſons of the Miniſters (though God, whereſoever he hath on earth a Church to gather, or to perfect, he will have a Miniſtry, even in deſpite of Hell it ſelf, unto the end of the world) but of the very Doctrine of the Goſpel: And is it not too true, that as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> proſecuted <hi>Iſaac, Gal:</hi> 4.29. ſo it is now: if any profeſſe but a* deſire to keep conſcience void of offence towards God &amp; man is commonly* the by-word of the People. Brethren, theſe are fearfull ſteps, I may not ſay of malice, for then I would trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yea I am forbidden in my Text, to pray for men ſo ſinning: But thus far many have gone, O let ſuch la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to recover themſelves. <hi>Faxit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto of the firſt, and generall uſe of this point:<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 13.18.</note> I come now to apply it with a more particular reſpect unto ſuch of Gods ſervants as have a more ſpecial in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſt in his favour, ſuch as are actually regenerate,<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 24.16 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2.</note> and born of God. Deareſt Chriſtians, this is that which may prevent your own diſcomfort, that iſſues many times out of groundles fear, leſt your ſtate be as that of thoſe guilty of this ſin, hopeles in ſuch ſort, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry infirmities, eſpecially where hath been knowledg of Duty, and perhaps ſome reluctation of conſcience,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:38129:17"/>are cenſured this great ſin: But take heed, bear not falſe witnes againſt thy ſelf, yea or againſt the truth of the promiſes, and of that<note n="a" place="margin">Jer. 32.40.</note> everlaſting Covenant of grace made to thy ſoul, and<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.20</note> ratified in the<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> blood of Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe bloud ſpeaketh<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> better things then the blood of <hi>Abel; Abels</hi> bloud<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 12.24.</note> cryed unto Heaven or vengeance, but the<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 4 10.</note> blood of Chriſt for mercy:<note n="f" place="margin">1 Joh. 1.7.</note> Know thou this, whoſoever thou art that indeed fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt God in<note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12.</note> ſimplicity of heart, ſo long as a man holds the way of righteouſnes in the courſe of his life, though (like the exorbitancy of a wheel, temptation may juſtle him out of the track) he have his ſteppings aſide in particulars, yet hereof let him be ſecure, this ſin he is not fallen into, for that implies an utter for ſaking of the whole,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21</note> way of righteouſnes: and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſo long as we keep in us the love of Gods truth, and of Gods Children, for truths ſake, we are out of gunſhot of this ſin: yea, if God at any time<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25.</note> give thee repentance for any ſin which thou haſt-commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, conclude it not this great ſin, which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death.</p>
            <p>And yet poſſibly, it may ſometime ſo fall out (for as in Water face anſwereth to face, ſo the Heart of Man to Man, <hi>Preverbs</hi> 27.19. and it hath been the caſe of divers others, even renowned Saints) I ſay it may ſometimes befall a godly ſoul, what it did to <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>Heman;</hi> the one <hi>Pſal:</hi> 77.7.8.9. paſſionately bemoaning himſelf, and dolefully putting the queſtion, (as ſpeaking after his preſent ſence.) <hi>Will the Lord caſt off for ever? and will he be favourable no more? Is his mercy clean gone for ever? doth his promiſe fail for evermore? Hath God forgotten to be gracious? hath he in anger ſhut up his tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies? Selah.</hi> Compare <hi>Pſalm:</hi> 38. and alſo <hi>Pſalm</hi> the 6. and <hi>Pſalm</hi> 32.3, 4. and the other almoſt throughout the whole 88th <hi>Pſalm</hi> complaineth of the<note n="*" place="margin">Lam. 3.44.</note> clouds
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:38129:17"/>from heaven, yea of the very<note n="(f)" place="margin">Job 26.14.</note> thunder of Gods power and wrath ratling over him, and ſenſibly felt in his ſoule within him: <hi>O Lord God of my ſalvation, I have cryed Day and Night before thee, O encline thine eare unto my Cry, for my ſoule is full of troubles, thy wrath lyeth hard upon me, and thou haſt afflicted me with all thy waves,</hi> Selah. <hi>Mine eye mourneth by reaſon of affliction:</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Lord, why caſteſt thou off my ſoule? Why hideſt thou thy face from me? I am afflicted, and ready to dye from my youth up, while I ſuffer thy terrours, I am diſtracted; thy fierce wrath goeth over me, thy terrours have cut me off.</hi> Beloved, here under theſe mournfull expreſſions ye ſee what<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iob 3.5. Ioel 2.6.</note> blackneſſe now was upon the perplexed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits even of theſe great Saints of God, for the preſent time: and to the ſame effect is that of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> Iſa. 38.14, 15. <hi>Like as a Crane or a ſwallow, ſo did I chatter, I did mourn as a Dove, mine eies faile with looking upward: O Lord, I am oppreſſed, undertake for me, and eaſe me, — I ſhall goe ſoftly all my years, in the bitterneſſe of my ſoule.</hi> In like manner St. <hi>Paul</hi> of himſelfe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5. <hi>Wee were troubled on every ſide, without were fightings, within were feares.</hi> And this many times is very much occaſioned by entring Compariſons of our owne ſtate with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, on whom (as we think)<note n="h" place="margin">Job 29.3. Pſal. 50.2.</note> God ſhineth altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo we entertain conceits, as if the Lord had clean croſs'd us out of his Book, that he<note n="(i)" place="margin">Job 30.20.</note> regards us not at all; that he looketh upon others, but paſſeth by us like a<note n="(k)" place="margin">Jer. 14.8.</note> ſtranger, to whom we are not known: Then we think our owne caſe to be<note n="*" place="margin">Lam. 1.12.</note> none ſuch, when we take Ieiſure to looke upon others, and comparing them with our ſelves, ſay their<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal, 23.5.</note> Tables are furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed day by day, whilſt earth and<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſal. 42.3.</note> aſhes and teares are our bread; they<note n="(n)" place="margin">Amos 6.5.</note> ſing to the Lute, and to the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ole, and they ſee their children<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 17.14.</note> dance before them; and (as that not more learned, than devout Divine M.<note n="†" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hooker;</hi> treat: of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of Faith in the Elect, <hi>p.</hi> 95.</note> (<hi>Hooker</hi> goes on, in flowrs of heavenly Rhetorick to ſet this out) our hearts are heavy in our bodies as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:38129:18"/>lead, our ſighes beat as thick as a ſwift pulſe, our tears<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 6.6.</note> do waſh the beds wherein we lye, whilſt others waſh in their paths in<note n="(p)" place="margin">Job 29.6. Job 29.3.</note> butter, as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith: The Lords candle ſhineth faire upon their foreheads; wee are hanged up like<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſ. 119.83.</note> bottles in the ſmoak,<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 31.12.</note> caſt into corners like the ſherds of a broken pot: Tell not us of the promiſes of Gods favour, tell<note n="*" place="margin">For my own part, I, in ſuch a caſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> if in any, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſpiritual things are if not odious, moſt diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable) I ſhould adviſe a diſconſolate ſoule, not to judg, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſtate by anothers mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but by his own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, and ſoundneſ, and to conſider himſelfe not by the degrees of inherent ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification by way of vigorous exerciſe, (which may be interrupted, <hi>Mar.</hi> 4.40. in himſelf) but by the ſtability of Gods donation, or gift of that grace in it ſelf, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is irrevocable, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. and then reſt confident, that (as Dr. <hi>Field</hi> expreſſeth it (<hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7, 8. of the Church) ſaving grace winneth infalibly, holdeth inſeparably, and leadeth indeclinably, of which whoſoever is partaker ſhall undoubtedly be ſaved.</note> [ſuch] as do reape the fruit of them, they belong not to us, they are made to others. Now Brethren, the Lord be mercifull to our weakneſs, but thus it is ſometimes: But thou wilt now ſay unto me, what muſt my demeanour be under this ſad diſtemper of my ſpirit, thus as <hi>Davids, Even o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelmed within me,</hi> Pſal. 142.3. Why, do thou as thoſe very Saints of God (in the like condition before thee) did; review <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.10. After the Prophets la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, upon his more adviſed thoughts, he ſaid, it was his [infirmity] ſo to do, and then he called to remembrance the yeares of the right hand of the moſt High: The right hand is both the ſtrongeſt, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the moſt ready to uſe, upon all occaſions; ſo with the Lord moſt high there is an omnipotent power<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Iſa. 26.4. Iſa. 63.1.</note> an everlaſting ſtrength, and, <hi>He is mighty to ſave, the</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 103.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſloweſt to conceive a wrath, and readieſt to forgive a ſinne: Tam pater nemo, Tam pius nemo,</hi> Tertul. Take the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles counſel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32.35. <hi>Caſt not therefore away your confidence, which hath great recompence of reward;</hi> Chide down thy diffidence and diſtruſtfull paſſions, and ſay, <hi>Why art thou thus caſt downe ô my ſoule? and why art thou diſquieted within me? Hope thou in God, for I ſhall</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yet there is hope left thee. St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle ſaid it in the <hi>Ecleſiaſt. Hiſt.</hi> to a wild yong man, <hi>Ez.</hi> 10.2.</note> 
               <hi>[yet] praiſe him, who is the health of my countenance, and my God,</hi> Pſal. 42.11. &amp; 43.5. What? do not the promiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:38129:18"/>to thee? a<note n="(r)" place="margin">Pſal. 116.16. Num. 12.7, 8.</note> ſervant? a<note n="ſ" place="margin">Jam. 2.23. Joh. 15.14, 15.</note> friend? yea, a<note n="(t)" place="margin">Rom. 8.14.17. Heb. 12.7.</note> ſon, yet more, an heire, a joynt-heir with Jeſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? and by that means<note n="(u)" place="margin">Pſal. 34 7. Cant. 6.8.</note> encompaſſed with a guard of heavenly<note n="(w)" place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> Angels, even Angels of<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pſalm. 103.20. &amp; 2 Theſ. 1.7.</note> might, and power to protect thee againſt all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Hell, and darkneſſe? To whom but unto thee, who art a regenerate ſoule, doth that promiſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine<note n="(y)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee;</hi> there are five Negatives in the Greek repeated, to aſſure Gods people, that he will never forſake them; it may be rendred according to the Greek (as one doth it) <hi>I will not not leave thee, neither will I not not forſake thee:</hi> Repetitions are no vaine Tautologies in holy Writ, they are uſed as <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> dreams were<note n="(z)" place="margin">Gen. 41.32.</note> doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, to aſſure the Saints of the more certain confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of what the Spirit of truth hath ſpoken: To thee, I ſay belongeth that rich, and<note n="(a)" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note> precious, even honourable promiſe of Almighty God; alas! alas! 'tis not for ſwine to expect ſuch pearls to be caſt away up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.6. This is a teat of comfort onely for the Child to ſucke, even to<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa. 66.11.</note> ſuck out and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, as from the breaſts of Conſolation; this is not meate for every mouth, but a choſen moyſture provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for Gods Inheritance only; this is Wine of Gods owne Cellar, layd up for his Spouſe alone, that is, for the devout ſoule dedicated unto Gods ſervice: Wherefore lift up the hands w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> hang downe, and the feeble knees, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12. O take heed of that ugly ſin, of all others the moſt odious, and black in the eyes of that God whoſe glorious grace<note n="(c)" place="margin">Rom. 5.20.</note> ſuperaboundeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mans ſin, I meane that monſtrous ſinne of Deſpair, by which <hi>Judas</hi> the Traytor ſinned more (ſaith an ancient Father) than by betraying his Lord, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt; and therefore was it that S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> gave the lye to <hi>Cain,</hi> when under the guilt of his awakened con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience he cryed out, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.13. <hi>My ſinne is greater then can be borne, Mentiris Cain,</hi> ſaith that devout Father,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:38129:19"/>who himſelfe, by his own Confeſſions (after the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies of a vaine youth, wherein he followed too much the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Eccl. 11.9.</note> fight of his eyes, experimented the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thoſe overflowing mercies, which do ſo much<note n="(e)" place="margin">Jam. 2.13.</note> rejoyce, and triumph, as it were, above judgment; Mercy flowing from the God and<note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.3.</note> Father of all comfort as water doth from a Spring or Fountaine moſt genninely, and freely; but Juſtice comes forth as liquor from the Wine-preſſe, when the grapes are ſqueezed, and after a ſort<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 40.11.</note> wrung out from him hardly; God doth not afflict willingly <hi>[delippo]</hi> or, from his heart, nor grieve the children of men, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.33. There was never any man periſhed for want of mercy in God, but for want of his owne repentance in himſelfe; as it was a ſin in the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to limit Gods power, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.41. ſo is it alſo to limit his mercy; What ſin can be imagined or committed too great for God to pardon? Wherefore, once again let me exhort thee; Cruſh that Cockatrice of Deſpaire in the very firſt<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 59.5.</note> Eggs thereof, and daſh that Babyloniſh brat in<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 137.9.</note> infancy. Beloved,<note n="*" place="margin">Deſperation what it is.</note> Deſparation is a kind of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or affection growing out of the ſenſe of ſin and wrath, it is <hi>malum arduum inſtans, &amp; ineluctabile,</hi> as one ſtileth it, and ordinarily it proceedeth from the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging of Gods affection, and good will towards men, the ſoule conceives of him, as of one that hath utterly caſt off all care, or reſpect towards it; whereas <hi>the LORD himſelfe is thy keeper, the LORD is thy ſhade upon thy right hand,</hi> Pſal. 121.4, 5. and hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee to commit the keeping of thy ſoule to him, in well-doing, as unto a faithfull Creator, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.19. And by ſo doing, we have all a ſure promiſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. To be kept by the power of God, through faith and ſalvation, <hi>A ſalvo conſervantis conductu, non â vacillante conſervati progreſſu:</hi> as an Orthodox<note n="(i)" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Prid.</hi> Lect. 6. Sect. 2.</note> Divine gloſſeth thoſe words; <hi>We are kept by the ſaving guidance of God the Keeper, and not left to the wavering unſteady progreſſe of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:38129:19"/>our ſelves, who are kept by him.</hi> What ſhall I ſay more? ſooner (ſaith a reverend<note n="k" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>King</hi> Lect. 26. on <hi>Jon:</hi>
               </note> Divine) ſhall God forgive the Apoſtacy of the Reprobate, lapſed, and damned Angels, then this damned ſinne of Deſperation: Give me leave among many (that I may contract this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) to preſent to you one Meane, or Remedie to prevent, or elſe to remove this evill; Which evill, if given way unto (through the inveterate malice, and envy of the Devill) it may like that<note n="l" place="margin">Iona 4.7.</note> worm in <hi>Jonah's</hi> Gourd in a night, eate out all the very ſap, and life of divine comfort: the Mean is this,<note place="margin">A remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt deſpair.</note> Diligent and prudent obſervation of Gods dealing w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> others of his ſervants finning though grievouſly in particulars; and withall of our owne perſonall<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 77.10, 11. Heb. 10.32.</note> experiences that (in former times) we our ſelves have had of Gods goodneſs in our own ſouls;<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 5.4.</note> Experience is the nurſe of Hope; <hi>Per ea, quae agnoſcas praeſtita, diſcas ſperare promiſſa,</hi> by thoſe things which you have known performed, learn to hope for thoſe things which are promiſed; to which meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on let us alſo joyne the ſerious conſideration of that glorious Attribute in God, his<note n="*" place="margin">If a man have received true aſſurance of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, though but once in all his life: yet by that one figne, he may aſſure himſelf of his ſalvation, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ground, <hi>John</hi> 13.1. that Gods love is unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, though ever after we live in temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Perk.</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23.</note> Immutability and unchangeableneſſe, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17. and that in reſpect both of his power and goodneſſe: make this reckoning, that the Benefits which he hath beſtowed, are (ſaith judicious <hi>Hooker</hi>) as it were bils obligatory, and ſufficient Sureties, that he will beſtow<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 25.29.</note> further; Neither is his hand<note n="o" place="margin">Num. 11.23 Iſa. 50.2. &amp; 59.1.</note> ſhortned, or his good will, no nor doth he faile to [remember] his Covenant of love made with Believers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.5. <hi>The Lord,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>is not unrighteous to forget,</hi> Heb. 6.10. As his hand is not ſhortned, ſo neither his arme weakned, that it cannot ſave as it hath done; <hi>Hee is the ſame ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, and to day, and for ever to his choſen,</hi> Heb. 13.8. His paſt, or preſent mercy is ſtill a warrant of his future love, becauſe <hi>whom he loveth, he loveth unto the end,</hi> John 13.1. Underſtand it <hi>amore benevolentiae,</hi> with the love of benevolence; though not <hi>amore beneficentiae,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:38129:20"/>of the manifeſtation of actual benificence he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw for a time his hand.</p>
            <p>And that I may ſhorten the way, by Examples, which ſeemeth often too long, by Precept; I ſhall offer two, and thoſe moſt notorious to your conſideration: One is of <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, and the other of <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene,</hi> out of whom it's ſaid that the Lord had caſt no leſſe then ſeven devils: <hi>Goe,</hi> ſaith the Angel, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.7. <hi>to the woman, who came to ſee the Sepulchre wherein Chriſt was laid; Goe your way, tell his Diſciples, and Peter, that he goeth before you into Galilee, there ſhall yee ſee him, namely, after his Reſurrection.</hi> Why is <hi>Peter</hi> here menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by name more, or rather than any of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſciples or Apoſtles? ſurely it was a ſpecial dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and act of grace in Chriſt, to ſingle him out by his name; as is obſervable in God toward his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite <hi>Jacob,</hi> Iſa. 43.1. <hi>Feare not, ô Jacob, for I have redeemed thee, I have called thee by thy [Name] thou art mine:</hi> Now <hi>Baronius</hi> and the Fry of the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, from this priority of Order wherein S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was now preferred, in a perſonall nomination, would coyne an argument for the oecumenical, univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal ſupremacy of the Pope, as the alone viſible Monarch of the whole catholike Church diſſeminate all the <hi>world</hi> over, uſurping withall an uncontroulable juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over all powers and conſciences, by pretending to a perſonall ſucceſſion of <hi>Peter</hi> in the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> although indeed he reſemble him in nothing rightly, but in the<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 26.70.</note> denyal of his Maſter: But away with thoſe paraſites of that<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.3.</note> man of ſinne, and leaving thoſe bladders of Antichriſtian haughtineſſe and pride, to be cruſhed by the feet of that ſupream head of his Church,<note n="q" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.22.</note> who is now haſtning to the<note n="r" place="margin">Rev. 17.1.</note> Judgement of the great Whore; <hi>Amen, even ſo</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rev. 22.20.</note> 
               <hi>come, Lord Jeſus, come quickly:</hi> O how would it joy thy Saints to ſee her lye in the<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pſal. 7.5.</note> duſt. I wis, there is other honey which the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Bees may ſuck from the ſweet flower of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:38129:20"/>of <hi>Peter,</hi> who had the honour, and happineſſe to be thus ſaluted, before others, after his Saviours Reſurrection: <hi>Goe and tell Peter!</hi> Would any one have thought <hi>Peter</hi> in a capacity of regard from Chriſt, whom againſt a ſolemn<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 26.33.35.</note> proteſtation to the contrary he had denyed, and abjured, even then too, when his fidelity to his Lord and Maſter ſhould ſpecially have appeared in the time of his ignominy, and reproachful uſage by his cruell Judges: Yes, my deare Brethren, <hi>ob hoc ipſum, quià gravius deliquit,</hi> as <hi>Granatenſis,</hi> with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry others, obſerveth, for this very cauſe, for that he had more grievouſly fallen, yet having<note n="w" place="margin">Mat. 26.75.</note> wept bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after that fall, and repented for it; hence it was, that upon that planck of Repentance, after ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a falling, he ſwam ſafe againe to the ſhoar of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and was received to mercy: The like meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo may ariſe out of the ninth verſe, from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> out of whom he had caſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven devill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to this very <hi>Mary,</hi> and that (which much heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the Emphaſis) to her too [firſt] before to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, yea before he appeared, for ought we read in Scripture, to <hi>Mary</hi> his Virgin Mother; Firſt, to a woman, that as a woman had been<note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.14.</note> firſt in the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, ſo ſhould ſhe be the firſt who partook in the manifeſtation of the compleat Redemption; when our Saviour by his riſing from the dead gave an<note n="y" place="margin">Acts 17.31.</note> aſſured e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and an infallible proof, that all the debt which was due to Gods Juſtice for the ſins of Believers was now fully diſcharged, in that Chriſt their ſurety, who undertooke to ſatisfie, was acquitted from the priſon of the Grave, the payns of death being looſed, becauſe it was not poſſible that we ſhould be holden of it, <hi>Act</hi> 2.24. Look then, as the woman that was made of a man, brought in ſin, and death, ſo the man that was made of a woman, brought in righteouſneſſe and life:</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:38129:21"/>
            <p>But was it not ſtrange, that our Saviour ſhould above all other women in the world, ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and all this favour to <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> one who had been ſuch a loathſome ſinke of uncleanneſſe, that ſeven devills, or a multitude of heynous crimes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed her whole ſelfe, as if ſhe had lyen down wholly under the full power and dominion of all, or moſt of the devills in Hell; Yet, firſt, to <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> out of whom hee had caſt ſeven devills: Surely this was done, ſaith <hi>Janſenius,</hi> and with him many Divines, <hi>In conſolationem paenitentium,</hi> to be for the infinite comfort of poor Penitents; as <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> had curled (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) and criſped her frizled locks for wanton dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, and luſtfulneſſe, ſo being forgiven much upon her Repentance, ſhe teſtified her love to that Saviour who had pardoned her, by<note n="z" place="margin">Luk. 7.38.</note> wiping his feet with the hair of her head, and waſhing them with her teares, cleanſing thoſe unchaſt, and adulterous<note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 9.21.</note> windowes, by which Death had entred, and ſo often endangered her ſoule to damnation: So true is that ſweet medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of St.<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Cyprian, De Caena Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, Sect. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian,</hi> upon the gracious act of Chriſt in pardoning the penitent Thief on the Groſſe, about his laſt expiration, <hi>quecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> neceſſitas cogat ad poenitudinem, Nec quantitas Criminis, nec brevitas temporis nec vitae enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitas, nec Horae extremitas, (ſi vera contritio, ſi pura fuerit voluptatum mutatio) excludit a venia;</hi> That is, neither the greatneſſe of the Crime, nor the enormity of the life, nor the extreamity of the laſt howre, provided that Cordiall, and ſerious Repentance ſeaſonably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervene, and come in between ſin and judgment, none of all theſe doe exclude from favour, and mercy from agracious God, who ſo often<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 10.20. Pſal. 21.3.</note> prevents a ſinner with the offers of attonement; when a poor penitent ſeems to be as it were, at a loſſe in a kind of wilderneſſe, then ſounds the horn of ſalvation for his returne to God, who embraceth him returning, returning (I ſay) yea, though it be after a long<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 56.8.</note> wandring out of the wayes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:38129:21"/>of righteouſneſs; to which purpoſe is that we read of in the Canticles, <hi>Cant:</hi> 6.13. <hi>Return, return, O Shulamite, return, return;</hi> every ſin is an averſion, or a turning from the Creator to the creature; but every act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is a<note n="*" place="margin">Mal. 3.7.</note> returning of the ſinner from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture unto the Creator back again; ſo here <hi>Quater dicit Revertere,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> He repeats this returning to the Shulamite foure times together; as if he had ſaid, Return from the original ſin of thy Nature, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from the actual ſins of thy life, return from thy ſins of cuſtome, and return alſo from thy ſcarlet, and from thy crimſon, and thine enormous tranſgreſſions; <hi>Quis non ſtupeat charitatem Dei ſpreti, &amp; revocantis?</hi> as the ſame Father; O admirable love, every finger of Chriſt drops myrrhe, and healing in this paſſage, in this one ſingle inſtance it ſhews it ſelf in all its dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, in the breadth, and length, and depth, &amp; height thereof, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.18. Who is not even ſtupified under the apprehenſion, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of ſo tranſcendent indulgence of the Lord from heaven to a miſerable, wretched, relapſed ſinner, who being offered love refuſeth, yea<note n="a" place="margin">Jer. 23.17. Act. 13.41.</note> deſpiſeth it, and yet ſuch, and ſo great is the Lords <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his free<note n="b" place="margin">Tit. 3.4.</note> love to mankind, that though they go<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 119.176. 1 Pet. 2.25.</note> aſtray like ſheep from the fold, where they might be ſafe, wandring amidſt<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> wolves, by which they are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be torn; yet, he<note n="e" place="margin">Pro. 1.24.</note> recals them back again unto himſelf in much love; and<note n="f" place="margin">Jer. 4.1.</note> if they will, though after a long expectation, and patience, but return at laſt to the<note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.25.</note> Shepherd and Biſhop of their ſouls; lo, he is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to meet them in kindneſs, who meet him in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, <hi>Iſa</hi> 64.5. Yea, as <hi>Calvin</hi> obſerves upon the carriage of the Father towards the repentant prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal ſon returning, <hi>Redeuntem eminus agnoſcit, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eb viis u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nis amplectitur,</hi> Luk. 15.20. when his ſon was yet a great way off, and had but <hi>h</hi> purpoſed as it were in his heart to ariſe, and go back to his Father (for I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:38129:22"/>underſtand this parable of one who had been already formerly in communion with the Church) his father ſaw him, and had compaſſion, and ran, and fell on his neck, and kiſſed him in all the poſtures of love embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, welcoming, entertaining of him, and rejoycing in his return home: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as moſt ſweetly<note n="i" place="margin">Athanaſius, qu. <hi>78.</hi> tom. <hi>2.</hi> pag: <hi>296.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> to the ſame effect, No ſin is irremiſſible, and unpardonable to any ſoul, that in an holy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner repenteth, and brings forth fruit<note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 3.8.</note> meet for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; not to him who blaſphemeth ſimply, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath it, but, unto him who abideth, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth under that fin, without remorſe impenitently is forgiveneſs denyed, who ſo finally perſiſts under ſuch a ſtate, he it is, who finneth unto death.</p>
            <p>Well, I perceive tis time to end, and I doubt leſt I weary your patience; and yet I have one word more to<note n="*" place="margin">Dent. 32.2.</note> drop for comfort to a regenerate ſoul, which is like to that wine made by Chriſt at the marriage Feaſt at <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Gallilee,</hi> perhaps the<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 2.10.</note> good kept til laſt. And that word is his, which I wiſh imprinted even in chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of gold, indelebly upon the hearts of every true <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> and <hi>Iſralite</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 1.47.</note> indeed: This is that I would ſay, this blaſphemy of the Holy Ghoſt, (ſo explained as ye have now heard it) this ſin, which is thus ſaid to be unto death? this ſin I ſay is not incident at all into any one, whoſoever is elect, and born of God, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to ſuch an one, there is no danger of final con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.1. Becauſe their ſins though dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their own nature, yet are not ſo in the event to them.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe that for divers good ends, that the<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.10.</note> God of all grace intendeth thereby, the choiceſt of Gods own People are ſometimes under great diſtreſſes,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 118.5.</note> ſhut up as it were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in a<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 88.8.</note> ſtraight place, out of which they ſee not how to come forth; and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:38129:22"/>howſoever the Lord will in the event, cauſe all to work together for their ſpirituall good;<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.28. 2 Chron. 32.31.</note> yet whilſt the ſerenity of Gods countenance is clouded as to them, whether for their<note n="b" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.7. zech. 13.9.</note> triall, or elſe for the * chaſtning of ſome particular Delinquency, or for the * quickning of graces languiſhing, or other like end, which in his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite wiſdome he aimeth at; I ſay,<note n="c" place="margin">Job 5.17.</note> during that ſtate,<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.30 for this cauſe.</note> miſerable are the perplexities wherewith they are ſurprized;<note n="e" place="margin">Hoſ 5.15.</note> but eſpecially if the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 6.3.</note> ſoul be alſo ſore vexed under ſome preſent apprehenſion of wrath by reaſon of ſome ſin committed againſt knowledg, and conſcience, then that wounded ſpirit who can bear? ſaith <hi>Solomon; Prov.</hi> 18.14. alas none, iniquities char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged [there] are too<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 38.4.</note> heavy to be born; in ſuch a caſe, all outward comforts are but as the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 58.9.</note> cracklings of thorns under a pot, without ſolid heat, or any laſting light: A Crown of Gold, though dec'kt with all the orient rubies of the higheſt value, cannot cure an aking head, nor a velvet ſlipper eaſe the torments of the gowt, nor any thing that is<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 9.1.</note> before them, or about them miniſter any joy, or refreſhing to them; And no marvel, becauſe there are in this evill of a perplexed conſcience, two things eminent above all others, which make it intoll erable, a wound not to be born; one is this, that whereas in all other afflictions man hath to do with man, or at the worſt with devils, in this he hath immediatly to deal with God himſelf:<note n="a" place="margin">Job 25.4. Pro. 20.9.</note> * polluted man with an * all pure God, ſinfull man with an * holy God,<note n="b" place="margin">Hab. 1.13.</note> offending man * with an angry God,<note n="c" place="margin">Joſh. 24.19.</note> who is in his wrath a conſuming fire;<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 7.11. and 76.7.</note> O the inexpreſſable agonies of a * deſolate ſoul,<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 12.29.</note> afflicted for the abſence of Gods ſmiles, tormented for the preſent ſence of his frowns for ſin! When God himſelf writes bitter things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a ſoul, the<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 143.4.</note> venome of his arrows muſt needs drink up the very ſpirit within him.<note n="i" place="margin">Lactant. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quid prodeſt non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere conſcium; habenti conſcientiam?</hi> ſaith<note n="g" place="margin">Job 13.26. Pro. 14.10.</note> 
               <hi>Lactantius,</hi> there needs no other teſtimony,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 1.9.</note> where God himſelf is a.<note n="h" place="margin">Job 6 4.</note> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:38129:23"/>and if the heart, that is the conſcience, condemn a man, God is greater than the heart, and knoweth all things, and will ſurely much more condemn him, being<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 34.7.</note> guilty: 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 3.20, 21. Now who (affected with the conſideration of his dreadfull Majeſty) can ſtand<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 90.7, 8.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God immediatly, when he is angry, and<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 76.7.</note> rebuketh man for ſin? What can that which is but finite do, in dealing with him who is infinite? where is no proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Secondly, whereas in other evils, a man is ſtill a friend to himſelf, in this caſe, he becomes a ſcourge, a magor-miſſabib, a fear round about, like <hi>Paſhur,</hi> a terror to himſelf. <hi>Jer:</hi> 20.4. and whatſoever is in him, all conſpires againſt him, underſtanding memory all: guilt in the conſcience is an importunate evill, and ſtill<note n="*" place="margin">Num 25.17. 2 Chro. 15.6.</note> vexeth as a <hi>Midianite</hi> was vexed, even as a thing that is raw reſtleſly: nor can we baffle, or put it off, as <hi>Faelix</hi> did Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who touched him to the quick, ſaying,<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 24.25.</note> go thy way for this time, and when I have a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſeaſon, I will ſend for thee; or if as thoſe that offe red their Children to<note n="n" place="margin">Jer. 32.35.</note> 
               <hi>Molech</hi> in fire, were wont with Drums to drown the noiſe, and ſcreeches of their little ones, in the valley of <hi>Hinnom,</hi> we think to ſilence it, its all in vain: Conſcience under the<note n="o" place="margin">Joh. 8.9.</note> conviction of ſin, and unpacified, its an ill companion in company, it daſheth all thy<note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 14.13.</note> pleaſures,<note n="q" place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> defileth all thy devotions. embitters all thy comforts, but a worſe when alone, Wherfore a ſoul that is in ſuch a caſe, (during the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the ſame) it ſits like a<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 102.6.</note> Pelican in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes,<note n="r" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.8.</note> deſolate diſtreſſed,<note n="s" place="margin">Pſal. 143.4.</note> perplexed.</p>
            <p>But yet my dear Brethren,<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 10.35.</note> caſt not away your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, but<note n="u" place="margin">Heb. 10.38.</note> live as the juſt man doth, that is, ought to do. By faith, one grain of living, vigorous faith may remove a Mountain of ſin into the Sea of forgetfulnes, which faith, ſaith the great Apoſtle, is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, the evidence of things not ſeen, <hi>Heb:</hi> 11.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the meaning is, that faith doth after a ſort give being, and a ſubſiſtence in the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:38129:23"/>ſoul to thoſe things, which being true in the promiſe of God, but yet not actually enjoyed, only are expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and hoped for: And in this ſad caſe, dwell ſeriouſly upon the meditation of the promiſes which have all their yea, and amen; their full ratification in the blood of Chriſt, the blood of the Covenant. Now look what is the promiſe? ſee (as ſeaſonable to this thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſad condition) <hi>Matt:</hi> 5.4. <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn for they ſhall be comforted. Pſal:</hi> 85.8. <hi>God the Lord he will ſpeak</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Note here, that Trouble of Conſcience is a good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative to peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (when ſanctified) &amp; indeed the ſolid true peace is brought out of former trouble Iſa. 61.1. Matt. 11.28. See Dr. <hi>Sclater</hi> Serm: <hi>Sick ſoul ſalved.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>peace unto his people, and to his Saints;</hi> provided they demean themſelves as Saints, <hi>viz:</hi> that after peace ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to them repenting for their folly, they do not again return to the ſame folly, ſee <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 2.14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.1.2. When God ſpeaks peace, his very ſpeaking is performing: <hi>Hath the Lord ſpoken, and ſhall not he do it?</hi> even <hi>Jehu</hi> could acknowledg ſo much,<note n="a" place="margin">Albertus No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicamp. in ſcopo Biblico, Annot. de Fide. Gerar. tom. <hi>3.5.75.</hi> tract. De Juſtif. per Fidem.</note> (being convinced of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular proof thereof,<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> know now ſaith he, there ſhall fall unto the earth, nothing of the Lord which the Lord hath ſpoken, I but thou wilt ſay, I feel no ſuch thing as peace ſpoken to my ſoul? ſuppoſe not in preſent ſence, yet it is moſt firm, and ſure in the promiſe of God; now live by faith, by beleeving thou layeſt a foundation; (ſo<note n="a" place="margin">We read Zech. 9.12. that the priſoners of hope were wiſhed to turn to theſtrong hold, and yet, at that time, there was har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly ary ſtrong hold, after the Captivi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, to turn to: to imply, that God was then the ſtrongeſt aid, when hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane helps af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, and then was the moſt proper ſeaſon for faith and hope to exerciſe their acts on warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able grounds.</note> ſome render, and expound the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) upon which to build the certain expectation of the promiſe, the more viſible things are, and obvious, or preſent to the ſence, the weaker is the faith, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency thereof is when it reſts upon the naked word, and authority of God the promiſer; which was exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified in <hi>Job.</hi> Chap: 13.15 <hi>Though the Lord kill me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>yet will I truſt in him,</hi> and in <hi>Abraham</hi> know that Gods power was perfected in the truth, though weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his ſervants faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. he ſtood not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring upon the weaknes, or unlikely hood of ſecond cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to produce, or accompliſh an iſſue, when both him ſelf and his Wife were, through natures debility, paſt all expectation of a Son, but he ſtill looked upon the ſtedfaſtnes of the promiſe, for the truth, and word ſake
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:38129:24"/>of the moſt faithfull promiſer, and ſo obtained the thing promiſed. <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.19.20.21. Faith made the Son as it were actually preſent to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as if he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed him before he was born, or begotten; for which cauſe its added alſo, that its <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an evidence, that is, as the word exactly imports, a convincing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration in the ſoul of the certain truth of what is promiſed;<note n="*" place="margin">Bonadventur: Diſt: <hi>23.</hi> qu: <hi>5.</hi> l: <hi>3.</hi> &amp; Joh: Altenſtaig. in Lexic. Theolog. y: <hi>61.</hi> in verbo Argumentum, &amp; pag: ib. <hi>326 327.</hi>
               </note> its tranſlated by <hi>b</hi> ſome, <hi>argumentum,</hi> the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of things not ſeen, for that it ſerveth ſo convincingly, to enlighten the mind, and to give aſſent to what is promiſed, as firmly as a true argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by ſtrength of reaſoning, occaſions an aſſent to the concluſion proved by it: Moreover, in caſe of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which Sathan raiſing ſtorms and tempeſts in the ſoul, may occaſion, then God hath provided, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us an Anchor both ſure and ſtedfaſt:<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 7.27.</note> 
               <hi>Heb:</hi> 6.19. that however we may be toſſed by temptation, yet our ſhip ſhall not be broken by the Waves, or ſplit againſt the Rocks.</p>
            <p>So then haſt thou finned?<note n="d" place="margin">Pro. 28.13.</note> confeſſe and forſake it, and God is righteous to<note n="e" place="margin">1 Joh. 1.9.</note> forgive it, canſt thou confeſſe it? and haſt thou a full<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 11.23.</note> purpoſe of heart to leave it, and to cleave unto the Lord? then be aſſured of this, thou haſt not committed the ſin; yea the very diſcovery within thy ſelf of thy ſin, and the<note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10.</note> ſorrow of heart thou conceiveſt for it, upon this ground, that<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 51.4.</note> God is offended by it, more than for any fear of puniſhment, hating ſin for ſins ſake, I ſay, this very diſcovery (cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption not being diſcovered by it ſelf, but by grace, as the Sun is not ſeen but by its own light) is a ſign that thou art not under the guilt of the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, for that ſin carries with it ſo deep an infatuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of * mind, and judgment, and withall ſo groſſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pefaction of conſcience, that the heart<note n="i" place="margin">Joh. 12.40. 2 Cor. 4, 4.</note> cannot repent, nor apprehend pardon. And to this purpoſe it is good for a ſoul diſtreſted to ſelect ſuch Texts of Scripture,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 2.5. Heb. 6.6.</note> as are moſt ſeaſonable for its own preſent ſtate, and with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:38129:24"/>all to conſider thoſe titles, or that ſtile which God is pleaſed to give himſelf, in relation to ſuch a ſtate of ſoul in his Children; thus he is called Rom. 15.13. <hi>The God of hope, now, the God of hope,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>fill you with all joy, and peace in beleeving, that ye may abound in hope through the power of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ſo alſo 2 Cor. 1.3 <hi>He is ſtiled the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Father of mercies, and the God of all cemfort:</hi> confer 2 <hi>Theſ:</hi> 2.16.17. It is a Chriſtians prudence to meditate likewiſe the tender regard he hath to the condition, and temper,<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 103.14</note> 
               <hi>k</hi> and frame of his Sons and Daughters under temptati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, God hateth nothing that he hath made, not a ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Matt:</hi> 10.29. not an Ox: 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 9.9. much leſſe man who is vertually all creatures: <hi>Mar:</hi> 16.15. ſee <hi>Tit:</hi> 3.4. read 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 10.13. <hi>There bath no temptation taken you, but ſuch as is common to man,</hi> [1 Moderate, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mans nature to undergo] <hi>But God is faithfull, who will not ſuffer you to be tempted above that you are able, but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that ye may be able to bear it, and if we beleeve not, yet he abideth faithfull he cannot deny himſelf.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.13. and again let us hold faſt the profeſſion of our faith without wavering, for he is faithfull that promiſed, and <hi>l</hi> that of <hi>John.</hi> 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 2. 1, 2. never be out of mind: <hi>My little Children, theſe things write I unto you, that ye ſin not: and if any man ſin, we have an advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous: And he is the propitiation for our ſins: &amp; not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world:</hi> compare <hi>Mat:</hi> 9.13. 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1.16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. Beloved Chriſtians, there is a kind of wiſdom and prudence in believing; thus conceive it. It is when a man fits the conſideration of the attributes, and actions of God to the particular moſt neceſſary, and fit for faith to reſpect, according to ſeverall occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: would they humble themſelves for their ſins? they then conſider God as terrible, and dreadfull in his Judgments? would they raiſe up themſelves with com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort? they conſider him as a God that keepeth promiſe:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:38129:25"/>would they ſtabliſh hope in expectation of things paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the courſe of Nature? they conſider his endles power,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 4.21. Eph. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>l</hi> able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we can ask or think: there is a confuſed aprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Diety (ſaith a R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>verend<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sclater</hi> my Father in his Comment on the <hi>Rom. cap.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 184. publiſhed by me, 1650.</note> Divine) for the moſt part liveles and ineffectuall; when men in groſſe only, and indiſtinctly meditate the Divine nature, without reference to particulars, concerning the preſent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And another as prepoſterous, and unſeaſonable; and no leſſe uncomfortable; when men fit their faith with meditation of that, that is moſt unſeaſonable, for their preſent ſtate; God is mercifull ſaith the Preſumer, He is juſt ſaith the deſperate diſtreſſed; Both true, he is juſt and mercifull ſaith the Pſalmiſt. But ſhould not faith in wiſdom contemplate what is fitteſt for the preſent neceſſity? this wiſdom pray we for.</p>
            <p>Dear Brethren, me thinks I would gladly (having travelled ſo much in this queſtion, for my own ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as well as yours) give<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 11.28.</note> eaſe to every weary ſoul, labouring under any perplexity, in this regard: But be ſure thou do, by al means, ſhun that grievous ſin of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, denying unto God the truth of his promiſe, and mercy, thoſe two ſweet attributes, wherein he doth much<note n="o" place="margin">Mic. 7.18.</note> delight to<note n="p" place="margin">See Exod. 34.6.</note> glory; his Juſtice in the viſitation of ſinners reacheth to the third, or fourth Generation; But his mercy is extended unto<note n="q" place="margin">Exod. 20.6.</note> thouſands, and endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 136.1, &amp;c.</note> for ever; there is obſerveable an holy writ, a three fold <hi>ſuper</hi> or [over] firſt, our ſins are [<note n="s" place="margin">Pſal. 38.4.</note> over] our heads, as an heavy, if not too heavy a burthen; then, Gods Judgments are [<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 10.5. Eccleſ. 5.8. Pro. 19.29.</note> over] thoſe ſins; But his mercies are [<note n="v" place="margin">Pſal. 145.9. &amp; Pſal. 36.5.</note> over] all theſe: over our ſins repented of to pardon them, over his Judgmets to remove them; and over our Bodies, and Souls, through the blood of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, everlaſtingly to ſave<note n="w" place="margin">Pſal. 98.2, 3.</note> them: Take heed, deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is of that haynous nature, that ſcarſly any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſin more diſhonors God, I am ſure none more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiets the ſoul; it often ariſeth from ignorance, or
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:38129:25"/>miſpriſion of the promiſes of God; that, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Gods exemplary dealings with other of his deareſt Saints (whereof I gave ſome intimation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) delivering them, even above their hope, out of how great perplexities, and (as to themſelves they ſeemed) even inextricable dangers and diſcomforts; Beſides ſome perſonall experiences, which St.<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.10. 2 Tim. 4.18.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> was wont to ſtay, and to ſupport himſelfe by, under the expactation of future mercies; I ſay, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this, men often miſtake the promiſes of God, ſometimes ſtreightning them to themſelves, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them more narrow then indeed they are; p e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption makes them over-wide, but deſpair too narrow; but eſpecially when they reſt too much and ſtick in the Duties required of them, as though the worke done did deſerve of God, or as if they were all exacted in the performance, after the rigour of the Law, which condemns every<note n="y" place="margin">Gal. 3.10.</note> interruption, or but<note n="z" place="margin">Jam. 2.10.</note> circumſtantiall breach, and defect; whereas indeed, they are<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> not <hi>under the law, but under grace,</hi> and the mitigation of the Goſpel, through Chriſt the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14.</p>
            <p>In a word, ſtabliſh thy Hope by theſe 3. Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which<note n="b" place="margin">Albertus No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicamp. ubi ſupra, <hi>tract. de ſpe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Albertus Novic.</hi> hath offered to us. 1. <hi>Veritate promiſſionis,</hi> by the<note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.18. Pſal. 93.3.</note> truth of the promiſe: <hi>Let God be true, &amp; every man</hi> [comparatively] <hi>a lyar,</hi> Ro. 3.4. <hi>He remaineth faithful,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. <hi>His covenant cannot fail, for it's everlaſting,</hi> Jer. 37.40. And of this Govenant He is likewiſe mindfull, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.5. Yea, when wee, under our <hi>Deliquiums,</hi> and as it were, inwar ſwoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of ſpirit, are apt to think <hi>He hath</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 77.9.</note> 
               <hi>forgotten to be gracious, and hath in anger ſhut up his tender mercies;</hi> yet, even then, he keepeth us in his mind; and, as the ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael</hi> acquaints us from experience, He <hi>[remembreth] us, even in our low eſtate, for his mercy endureth for ever,</hi> Pſal. 136.23. Only take heed of<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 78.41.</note> limiting the Lord to thine owne<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 1.7. 1 Theſ. 5.1.</note> time, <hi>He waiteth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:38129:26"/>to be gracious,</hi> but in his own ſeaſon; therefore in this regard, <hi>He that believeth,</hi> ſaith that Evangelicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.16. <hi>ſhall not make haſt:</hi> If God hath long waited for us, ſhall not we wait upon God<note n="g" place="margin">ſee Pſal. 27.14. Mic. 7.7, 8. Jer. 14.22.</note>? for though he tarry long [namely, as to thine owne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion] yet, when his own ſeaſon (which he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knows<note n="h" place="margin">Acts 1.7. ſee <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3.</note> when it is beſt) is come, then is <hi>He a very preſent helpe in trouble,</hi> Iſa. 46.13. Pſal. 46.1. And when he doth come indeed, he makes a large amends for his ſtay by doubling his comforts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.7, 8. And if we receive the witneſſe of men, ſurely the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God is greater, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7. 1 <hi>John.</hi> 5.9, 10. Wherefore, be confident of his Truth; onely ye have need of patience a while, that after ye have done the will of God, ye might receive the promiſe; <hi>For yet a little, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry,</hi> Heb. 10.36, 37. The occaſion of fainting in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, is defect in faith: <hi>I had fainted,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I had believed to ſee the goodneſſe of the Lord in the land of the living,</hi> Pſal. 27.13.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to ſtabliſh Hope by is, <hi>poteſtate red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionis,</hi> by the<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 4.21.</note> power of God actually exhibiting, and making good the promiſe; <hi>With God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gabriel</hi> the Angel (whoſe name ſignifieth the ſtrength of the mighty God) <hi>nothing ſhall be impoſſible,</hi> Luk. 1.37. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed whatſoever imports matter of impotency, and weakneſs, or what is repugnant, and contrary to the nature of his omnipotency, this God cannot doe, as to lye, to deny himſelfe, both theſe are impoſſible to God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.2. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.13. Looke then what God hath promiſed, the ſame ſaith <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> from a rare experience, and proof of his power, <hi>He is [able] alſo to performe,</hi> Rom. 4.21. <hi>Be ye therefore ſtrengthened with all might, according to his glorious power, unto all patience, and long-ſuffering, with joyfulneſſe,</hi> Col. 1.11.</p>
            <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. And laſtly, Hope is corroborate, and receiveth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:38129:26"/>ſtrength, <hi>charitate adoptionis,</hi> by the conſideration of the divine love of Adoption. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith that very Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whom Chriſt<note n="k" place="margin">John 13.23.</note> loved, &amp; who had his very boſome, <hi>what manner of love the Father hath beſtowed upon us, that we ſhould be called the ſonnes of God,</hi> 1 Job. 3.1. Rom. 8.15. <hi>Yee have not received the ſpirit of bondage again to fear, but yee have received the ſpirit of adoption, whereby we cry Abba, father,</hi> compare <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.5, 6. And now, my dear brethren, ſith, <hi>from being by nature Children of wrath,</hi> Eph. 2.3. <hi>Enemies to God,</hi> Rom. 5.10. <hi>Captives of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.26. We are under a ſtate of divine love, wee are in the hands of a dear Father, even as<note n="l" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.1.</note> dear children, and that <hi>He ſpareth us as a</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Mal. 3.17. Pſal. 103.13.</note> 
               <hi>father doth the ſon that ſerveth him,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Mic. 7.18.</note> paſſing by, &amp;<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 51.1.</note> hiding his face from many tranſgreſſions, which of<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 77.10. Gal. 6.1.</note> infirmity, or<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 116.11.</note> paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we may ſometimes be overtaken in; <hi>Give we thanks to his Father, which hath made us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light: Who hath delivered us from the power of darkeneſſe, and hath tranſlated us into the kingdome of his deare ſonne: In whom wee have redemption through his blood, even the forgiveneſſe of ſinns,</hi> Col. 1.12, 13, 14. <hi>Having then theſe</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1.</note> 
               <hi>promiſes, dearely beloved,</hi> and ſharing in ſuch priviledges as theſe are, I cannot but ſay with that Orthodox Father, S. <hi>Auſtin, Erigat ergo, ſe humana fragilitas,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148.</note> 
               <hi>non deſperet, non ſe collidat, non ſe vertat, non dicat, non ero, &amp;c.</hi> Let humane frailty ſtirre up it ſelfe, and not be<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 42.11.</note> caſt downe with deſpair, let it not break it ſelfe, or daſh upon that dangerous concluſion of <hi>[I ſhall not be]</hi> namely, <hi>in favour againe with God:</hi> What? never in favour? not a dearly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son with a dearly loving Father? Conſider, what is it that God hath promiſed thee? O thou mortall man, is it not<note n="u" place="margin">Joh 3.16.</note> life eternall? is it not that thou (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving) ſhouldſt be<note n="w" place="margin">Joh. 17.24.</note> where Chriſt the<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8.29. Col. 1.15.18. and 1.6.</note> Firſt-borne himſelfe is? O believe, believe, <hi>plus eſt quod jam fecit, quam quod promiſit,</hi> loe, ſaith<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Auguſt. l. <hi>13</hi> de Trin. <hi>c. 16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin,</hi> he hath actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally already done more (after a ſort) than what he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:38129:27"/>hath promiſed: Why, what hath God done? He hath<note n="z" place="margin">Phil. 2 8.</note> dyed for thee: and what hath he promiſed? that thou ſhalt live with him: <hi>Incredibilius eſt, quod mortuus eſt aeternus, quam ut in aeternum vivat mortalis,</hi> as the ſame Father; It is more incredible, that He who is eternall (though not as eternall) ſhould become mortall, than that He who is in his nature mortall, ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come eternall, to wit, in a ſtate of glory: Now the firſt of theſe wee believe, namely, that he who was God<note n="a" place="margin">Acts 20.28.</note> ſhed his blood, and dyed; why, then believe that God, <hi>who is rich in mercy, for his great love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he loved us, even when we were dead in ſinnes, hath quickned us together with Chriſt (by grace ye are ſaved) and hath raiſed us up together, and made us</hi> (in promiſe, in hope, and expectation) <hi>ſit together in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Eph. 2.4, 5, 6.</p>
            <p>But why am I thus tedious, and over-long? How canſt thou, under all theſe ſoule-chearing expreſſions, be ſtill dejected: conſider God the Father, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth life unto thee, hath ſtiled himſelfe <hi>The God of Conſolation,</hi> Rom. 15.5. <hi>Yea of (all) comfort,</hi> who comforteth his Saints in all their tribulations, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. And when they are caſt down, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.6. He is ſtiled by <hi>David, The God of my mercy,</hi> Pſal. 59.10. God the Son likewiſe is called <hi>The conſolation of Iſrael,</hi> Luk. 2.25. And God the Holy Ghoſt hath his Title to be the <hi>Comforter, abiding with Believers for ever,</hi> Joh. 14 17. &amp; Joh. 15.26. the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rendred out of the Originall, <hi>Comforter,</hi> ſignifieth (ſaith the learned <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi>) one who pleadeth the cauſe of another, who is a guilty perſon, as it were an Advocate; ſo that when a ſoule is under temptaion, or drouping for ſinne, the ſpirit of God the Comforter erecteth, cheareth, exciteth, and reviveth it by alledging, as it were, the Priviledges of the promiſes, which in the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and in the due application of them, eaſe the burthen of the Conſcience loaden with ſinne; the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:38129:27"/>ſpirit being therefore ſtiled <hi>The holy ſpirit of promiſe,</hi> Eph. 1.14. becauſe he cleareth, aſſureth, and<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.22. Epheſ. 4.30.</note> ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up the Title, and Confirmation of them to the ſoules of the Elect, co-witneſſing <hi>with their ſpirits, that they are the ſonnes of God,</hi> and ſo diſcharged, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16.33.</p>
            <p>And indeed, to hold you no longer in theſe ſo prolix amplifications, the very ſcope and aime of S. <hi>John</hi> in my Text, is to prevent, and to anticipate the feare of diſcomfort that probably might ſurprize the children of God about what he had ſpoken to uching the ſin which was unto death, for which no prayers were allowed for to implore the pardon of it; for whereas the very Saints themſelves found unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe (at leaſt in the remainders) within them, ſanctification in this life being only<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12. 2 Cor. 3.18. Phil. 3.13.</note> Inchoate, not Conſummate, and the Apoſtle expreſly granting, that all unrighteouſneſſe was ſin, leſt they might (privy to themſelves of ſinne (ſuſpect, out of a pious jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie) that that ſin in them might be this ſin unto Death, (chiefly when both in Judgment, and Conſcience they knew it to be ſin) therefore in the 18. <hi>verſe</hi> he affirms, <hi>that who ſo is borne of God ſinneth not,</hi> not ſimply, not at all; for in <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. including himſelf (though an Apoſtle) as well as other Saints, he declares ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, <hi>If we ſay that we have no ſinne,</hi> what then? not, we are proud, and ſo have no humility in us: <hi>But wee deceive our ſelves, and lye, and ſo the truth is not in us;</hi> and to the ſame purpoſe S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> makes his obſervation upon the conjoyning together of thoſe two Petitions in the Lords Prayer, <hi>Give us this Day our daily Bread, and forgive us our Treſpaſſes,</hi> that we might take notice of as much neceſſity that we had to begge of God the pardon of our daily treſpaſſes, as the ſuppeditation, and ſupply of our daily Bread: But his meaning is, <hi>He that is begotten, and borne of God, ſinneth not unto death,</hi> that great and unpardonable offence, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:38129:28"/>of the Holy Ghoſt? They cannot fall, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver are elected, and regenerate of the ſpirit of God, into that ſin, which becauſe, as ye have heard already, it is not (through Gods formidable Judgment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon) capable of repentance, no more is it of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or forgiveneſſe: Now all ſins being pardoned to the Elect, it follows, that they are beyond the reach or danger of this ſin which is ſaid to be (irreparably) unto death, and that not temporall only, but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. O royall priviledg! O mercy incomprehenſible! A regenerate ſoule ſinneth not unto death? Surely <hi>Solomon</hi> could not ſhew the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> ſo much trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in all the<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 6.29.</note> glory of his Kingdome, as is lapt up in theſe few words: and O that God would open this Arke of mercy, wherein this Doctrine lyeth, and ſet it wide before the eyes of poore afflicted Conſciences, which like <hi>Noah's</hi> Dove fly up and down upon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their afflictions, and can ſee nothing but only the gulfe, and deluge of their ſins, wherein there is no place for them to<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 8.9.</note> reſt their feet: I ſay, and pray, as devout <hi>Hooker,</hi> the God of Pitty, and<note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.3. Lam. 3.32.</note> Compaſſion, give every<note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 2.18. Gal. 6.1.</note> tempted ſoul faith, and ſtrength, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, every day, and every houre, and every moment, to embrace, and to lay hold upon this truth,<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 19.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſweeter by farre then honey, or the honey-combe,</hi> dropping and diſtilling, yea diffuſing comfort, even<note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>joy unſpeakable and full of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſoever then finds in himſelfe any ſound note of election,<note place="margin">Notes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation.</note> and regeneration, that man may aſſure himſelf he hath not committed, no nor<note n="k" place="margin">1 Joh. 3.9.</note> can commit this deadly, and unpardonable ſin: let me epitomize the larger enumeration of ſuch ſignes under the ſhort abridgment of theſe few heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Peccati diſplicentia,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Eze. 36.31. Rom. 7.15.</note> diſlike of ſin, godly<note n="m" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.10,11.</note> ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſin, ſtriving againſt ſin, though his falls have been fowle even againſt knowledg, he may be aſſured he is free from this ſin.</item>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:38129:28"/>
               <item>2. A ſecond may be <hi>Veritatis Amor,</hi> Cordiall<note n="o" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.11. Pſ. 119.20.97. Job 23.13.</note> love of Evangelicall Truth, if that ſtill be deare unto him, inſomuch as he would be content to buy it at any rate, but will ſell it at no rate, <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.23.</item>
               <item>3. A third is Faith, not only that which is called <hi>Fides quae,</hi> the doctrine of faith ſtaying in the Hiſtory and generall truth of the Goſpel, to which as many a Caſtaway hath attained, ſo likewiſe many an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate hath departed from it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. But that which is <hi>Fides quâ,</hi> the faith of Gods Elect, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. conſiſting not onely in a bare naked know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, but alſo in the acknowledging of the Truth, which is after godlineſſe, ſpecially applying the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of grace through Jeſus Chriſt to himſelfe in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. This faith, though<note n="*" place="margin">Eſt infirma fides, tamen, illa fides.</note> little in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the meaſure, yet being ſound in regard of the Truth, it's alike pretious in all the Saints, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1. nor will God quench the ſmoaking flax, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.20. Though there may for a time appeare more ſmoak than fire, yet whilſt there is fire, there is the ſpirit of all grace, but chiefly of faith in the truth thereof, which is an infallible fruit of Election, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.</item>
               <item>4. The laſt that I ſhall now name is the love of the Brethren, becauſe they are Brethren, for the very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſake of the truth of the Goſpel, not for any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall endowments, or morall habiliments,<note n="p" place="margin">2 Iohn <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> or for the meer emoluments, or ornaments of Fortune, all which are but <hi>pompatica, &amp; volatica,</hi> as one calls them, the trappings, and dreſſes, like unto flatulent chaffe, <hi>They take unto themſelves wings, and fly away:</hi> But when grace that ſhineth in them is the motive of our love, that is an evidence indeed of our being tranſlated from a ſtate of ſpiritual death, to the contrary condition, and ſtate of ſpiritual life, and ſalvation, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.14. If theſe things be in us, and abound, wee ſhall never fall from election, or (whilſt they are in their vigrous
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:38129:29"/>and predominant exerciſe) from the aſſurance of the ſame, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. Now, if we are aſſured of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that not only <hi>Certitudine objecti,</hi> as the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpeak, as it reſts in <hi>mente divinâ,</hi> in the mind of God, certain in it ſelfe; but likewiſe <hi>Certitudine ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti,</hi> as it is in the uſe of the right meanes, manifeſted to our owne breaſts by Gods ſpirit; we have then an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that we are in ſtate of preſent grace, and ſo are borne of GOD, and by conſequent ſinne not unto death.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ʋſe 2."/> I haſten now Brethren, for a ſecond Uſe, but very ſuccinctly, of what hath been thus enlarged upon this ſin; It may ſerve to reſtrain from all raſh, and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long cenſure of others, whoſe facts perhaps may be grievous, yet they for all that, not culpable of this great tranſgreſſion, it may be they perſecute, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Howbeit, inaſmuch as we know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it iſſue out of malice, at leaſt, though evidence be apparant of malice againſt our perſons; yet if not, for Grace-ſake, feare to cenſure of this ſin unto Death: It's not ingenuous to be like <hi>Porcupines</hi> darting quills of<note n="q" place="margin">Matth. 7.1. Luke 6.37.</note> cenſure on mens ſpiritual ſtates, or but doubtfull actions: the carriage of our Saviour towards the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>Phariſees,</hi> (who were ſtill angling after ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage againſt him, <hi>ſeeking to catch ſomething out of his mouth, that they might accuſe him,</hi> Luk. 11.54.) I ſay, his carriage towards them in the buſineſſe of the woman accuſed for being taken in the act of Adultery, <hi>John</hi> 8.8. is very remarkable; whilſt they continued asking of him what puniſhment ſhe deſerved, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to have ſurrounded him with a <hi>Dilemma,</hi> that if he had ſaid ſhe was to be ſtoned, he had been a med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in State matters, things criminall, and capitall; if not, then he had ſpoken againſt<note n="r" place="margin">Acts 6.11.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Law, and by that have brought himſelfe in danger; but our Saviour, to divert the importunity of ſo many intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling queſtions, <hi>v.</hi> 6, &amp; 8. <hi>He ſtooped downe, and with</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:38129:29"/>his finger wrote on the ground, as though he heard them not, many are the conjectures at what that ſhould be which he then wrote: Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his conceit was. that He wrote that ſentence, <hi>Matt:</hi> 7.3. <hi>Why beholdeſt thou the moat that is in thy Brothers eye, but conſidereſt not the beam that is in thine own eye. Beda</hi> gneſſed, that he wrote the ſentence which He ſpake, he that is without ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, let him firſt caſt a ſtone at He: <hi>Haymo</hi> ſeems more witty, than judicious in his apprehenſion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, He thinks he wrote certain Characters in the pavement, which the accuſers beholding, might ſee as in a glaſs their own wickednes, and ſo bluſhing at it, ſlunk away, in the conviction of their own Conſcience: But whatever it was ſure we are (ſaid once an eminent Divine of our Church) our Saviour would have falſe accuſations written in duſt, to be trodden under foor of thoſe that paſſe by, take we heed how we<note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 14.10.</note> judg raſh judgment of another mans ſtate, or conſcience, preſume not to ſit in Gods Conſiſtory, every man ſtands, or fals, in point of his ſouls judgment to the Supreme<note n="t" place="margin">Jam: 4.12.</note> Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver,<note n="v" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5.</note> Judg therefore nothing, before the time, that God, who alone judgeth<note n="w" place="margin">Joh. 7.24 1 Sam: 16.7.</note> righteous Judgment, doth diſcover all ſecrets, and actions, whether they be good, or whether they be evill: In the mean time, let us ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xt, that there is a ſin not unto death, as well as that which is ſaid to be unto death,<note place="margin">Spiritualia peccata gravio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſunt, quàm Carnalia: quia Spirituale pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum plus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>het de averſione, â Deo, &amp; Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalia peccata habent vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentius impulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum, viz. ipſam connatam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cupiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for which there is a warrant for us to pray, and upon our prayers (duly qualified) a promiſe to be heard for the life of our Brother repenting, there remains yet ſomething farther obſervable, out of the body of the Text, which I ſhall only intimate, and ſo conclude this diſcourſe for the preſent.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Apoſtle ſaith, there is a ſin, one unto death, and another not ſo, we may note a difference, and diſtinction of ſins, one is more haynous than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there are ſome ſtains: <hi>Cant:</hi> 4. and in <hi>Iſa:</hi> 1.18. ſins of a ſcarlet dye, ſome ſins againſt the Body: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:38129:30"/>others againſt the ſoul, <hi>Prov:</hi> 3.36. ſome <hi>y</hi> moats, and ſome beams, ſome<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Matt. 23.24.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Among the latine is a cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between</hi> pecc atum, cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſcelus, faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, flagitium, deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tum, viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, vid. Albert: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>camp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p. <hi>365.</hi> De Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie:</p>
                  <p>Facere non fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienda pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atum eſt, facienda non facere deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt, Hugo de S. victore, Allegor: in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od: l <hi>3.</hi> c: <hi>6.</hi> &amp; vitia flagiciis leviora ſunt. Aul: Gell: l. <hi>1.</hi> c: <hi>17.</hi> Noct: At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tict: Delictum eſt contra prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept: affirmat: Commiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, contra negati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum. Nic: de orbellis, in <hi>2</hi> Sent: Diſt: <hi>43.</hi> &amp; Lumbard: l: <hi>2.</hi> Diſt: <hi>42.1.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> gnats, and ſome Camels, ſome ſpots, <hi>Jud. v:</hi> 12. and ſome monſtrous clouts, <hi>Iſa:</hi> 64.6. There are ſins of incogitancy, or of ſudden ſurreption, as vain ſights that affect to ſome ill, or idle, and inde pendent thoughts, which have no conſiſtancy together, from ſuch ſecret, undetected ſins <hi>David</hi> prayed to be cleanſed: <hi>Pſal:</hi> 19.12. There are alſo ſins of ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, when the heart of the Sons of men is [fully ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>] in them to do evill: <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 8.11. There are ſins of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, for which attonement might be made, and there are other committed with an high hand more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly, and ſeverely to be puniſhed <hi>Numb:</hi> 15.30 <hi>Pſal:</hi> 19.12 13: There are ſins of infirmity. Pſal. 77.10. and there are ſome raigning: Rom: 6 12. Eph. 2.2, 3. ſome cuſtomary. Jer. 13.23. and there is a ſin, or blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of malice, which is unpardonable: In ſumme, ſins m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y be ſaid to ariſe in haynouſnes 3. manner of wayes. 1. <hi>Genere,</hi> in the kind of the ſin. 2. <hi>Gradu,</hi> in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of it. 3. <hi>Circumſtantiis,</hi> in the circumſtances. In the kind ſo ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> though theft be a ſin, yet adultry is more haynous, as appears by the penalty of both: <hi>Prov.</hi> 6 30.32. in the kind of it, its greater: ſo vain ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abominable, but falſe ſwearing is, in the kind more damnable, In the degree <hi>Mat:</hi> 5.22. Raſh anger a degree of murther, reproachfull railing higher, but actual em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruing hands in blood, ſtill much more enormous: wanton looks diſpoſe to adultry, unchaſt geſtures more, but the act of uncleanes fowleſt of all: In the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, ſome vary the kind of the ſin, as thus, theft of common things from men a ſin, but robbing God, <hi>Mal:</hi> 3.9 is a ſacriledg, and reducible under the breach es of the firſt precept,<note n="*" place="margin">Pet: 3.9.</note> railing at men a ſin, 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 6.10. but railing at God, blaſphemy. <hi>Matt:</hi> 12.31.32. There are alſo circumſtances, that though they vary not the kind of the ſin, yet add much to the aggravation of it; three only we may inſiſt on. 1. The motive. 2. The
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:38129:30"/>manner. 3. The iſſue. To perſecute of ignorance, as <hi>Paul</hi> did: 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 1.13. is much, but of malice more, the motive makes it ſo; to ſin of paſſion, inordinate, diſcom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortable, Pſal. 116.11. but to ſin wilfully more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous: Heb: 10.26. For the manner, to ſin in ſecret, Eph: 5.12. fearfull, but to declare ſins<note n="a" place="margin">Vid. Thom. <hi>1</hi> a, <hi>2</hi> ae, qu: <hi>73.</hi> Art. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> openly as <hi>Sodom,</hi> Iſa. 3.9. far more haynous; once to fail in duty to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it drunkenes, its ſinfull, but daily to add drunkenes to thriſt, Deut: 29.19. and to ſay, as thoſe ſwiniſh Athe iſts in the Prophet; <hi>Iſa:</hi> 56.12. <hi>Prov:</hi> 23.35. To morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more abundant, this ſtil heightens the odious abomination: For the iſſues, thus conceive,<note n="b" place="margin">Matt. 18.6, 7. Rom. 14.21.</note> ſcandalous ſins are greater, and thoſe by whom many<note n="c" place="margin">Omne animi vitium tanto coſpectius in ſe crimea habet, quanto major, qui peccat, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur. Juven: Rationes a. vid: apud Thom: <hi>1</hi> a, <hi>2</hi> ae, qu: <hi>73.</hi> Art. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> exemplary are defiled, <hi>Heb:</hi> 12.15. than others that ſtick in the perſon ſingly, and by himſelf: I might be very copious under theſe ſeverall head<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: But I conſider the great affairs now following.</p>
            <p>And indeed, this is the conſtant Doctrine of our Churches, however the<note n="d" place="margin">Hoc quoque tritum eſt in hâc faece Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium peccata eſſe paria; hâc. trutinâ non le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius in Deum deliquerit ille caupo qui gallum gallinaceum, quàm qui homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem occiderit. <hi>Campianus Jeſuit. Rat. 8.</hi>
               </note> Romane Catholicks charge us with a kind of ſtoichiſm in this point, as if we made all ſins equall: The<note n="e" place="margin">Hoc de pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilitate peccatorum ſoli Stoici auſi ſunt diſputare contra omnem ſenſum generis humani. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
               </note> ſtoicks, to whoſe Fate <hi>Tully</hi> in his Paradoxes ſeems to incline, had as the <hi>Jovinians</hi> ſince them a fond opinion, that all fins were equall, none more grievous than others, yea as greatly ſins He, <hi>Qui gallum gallinacium,</hi> as <hi>Qui Patrem interficit,</hi> who killed a Cock, as He who ſhew his Father; A ſentenſe deviſed by them, to keep men in more aw, and to make them have care to ſhun even the leaſt ſins, ſith al were of equal hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſnes among them; but indeed, it is the high way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o prophanes; and the Scripture is expreſſe againſt this parility, (as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> expreſſeth it) and for the * inequality of ſins,<note n="f" place="margin">Among the Greeks <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, differ; the one denoting every ordinary offence, and aberration from the right mark: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſin which is more enormous and deeply faſtened in a man, <hi>Sumitur pr gravi, &amp; incondonabili crimine, Grotius:</hi> ſo likewiſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>peccans, &amp; peccator,</hi> or as <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phan: peccatoſus, qui peccati habitum comparaverit. Beza.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Joh:</hi> 19.11. our Saviour ſaith
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:38129:31"/>of <hi>Judas,</hi> who delivered him into the hands, and power of <hi>Pilat,</hi> that h: had in the comparative, the [greater] ſin; there are bad: and there are worſe; 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 5.8. He that provideth not for his own, is [worſe] than an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell, 2 Pet: 2.20: and <hi>Matt:</hi> 12.45: the latter end is worſe than their beginning: <hi>Ezek</hi> 16.47. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was corrupted [more] ban <hi>Samaria</hi> in all her ways; and this appears alſo by the diverſi y that is in the degrees of puniſhment, our Saviour himſelf ſpeaks of a more eaſie, and a more tolerable ſtate at the day of Judgment. <hi>Matt:</hi> 11.22.24. there is a greater, and there is a leſſe damnation. <hi>Matt:</hi> 23.14. there are many, and few ſtripes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12 47.48. and though all ſins deſerve eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death, yet are not all ſinners equally tormented. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w God being a<note n="f" place="margin">Gen: 18.25. 2 Tim: 4.8.</note> righteous Judg, proportions the<note n="g" place="margin">Rev. 18.7.</note> meaſure of puniſhments according to the meaſure, and degree of ſinning; ſome ſins there are which the Lord out of hit<note n="h" place="margin">Mic. 7.18.</note> longanimity, and patience, after a ſort, paſſeth by as not ſeeing them, <hi>Act:</hi> 17.30. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, winking at them: But there are others ſo atrocious, as that they cry aloud to Heaven for vengeance, of which nature was the blood of <hi>Abel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clamitat ad coelum vox ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis, &amp; Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum, vox op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſorum, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</note> 
               <hi>Gen:</hi> 4.10. the grievous ſin of <hi>Sodom, Gen.</hi> 18.20. ſo likewiſe oppreſſion, <hi>Exod:</hi> 3.7 and 22, 23. and the defrauding labourers of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.4: there is a fulnes of iniquity, ſuch as the <hi>Amerites</hi> aroſe unto <hi>Gen.</hi> 15 16. and a meaſure to be filed up, <hi>Matt:</hi> 23 32. ſuch was that ſtate of the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Jews, on whom a proportion able fulnes of wrath came to the uttermoſt. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.16.</p>
            <p>But, however upon theſe teſtimonies, it be clear, that this <hi>Stoiſciſme</hi> be faſly charged upon our Churches; yet is the opinion (it ſerms) much amongſt our People, to whom all ſins are equal; we are all ſinners (ſay they) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but I trow not al Adulterers not alremorſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpenitent, ſinners: and they ſhall know, one day, that there is a difference of ſins, when God ſhal injudgment inflict heavier damnation.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:38129:31"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Queſt."/> To ſhut up all, if we teach not an inequality of ſins, how then is it (ſay <hi>Papiſts</hi>) that we ſay all are mortal, and none veniall?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſw."/> To this the anſwer lyeth thus, though the diſtinction of mortal, and veniall, be not in terms, ſo expreſſed, yet in ſenſe, it is contained under theſe words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>A ſin unto death, and a ſin not unto death:</hi> the odds is only in the manner of explication: venial ſins to them are all ſuch which are ſo in their own nature, as light matters out of incogitancy, and of ſurreption, or of humane infirmity, as impertinent thoughts, idle words, wanton glances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch as theſe are pardonable in themſelves, at moſt, are made expiable by ſome<note n="i" place="margin">Remiſſio ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nialis peccati nihil aliud eſt, quàm ſolutio poenae temporalis pro eò debitae. <hi>Scotus l. 4. Diſt. 21.</hi>
               </note> cem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary ſufferings, even without<note n="k" place="margin">Ad remiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem peccati ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nialis non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiritur paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia propriè accepta remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titura. veniale per Satiſpaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem in purgato rio. <hi>Biel, 4. ſent. diſt. 16. qu. 5 Art: 2.</hi>
               </note> repentance properly taken either here, or in purgatory, mortall, in their ſenſe, are ſuch only as are of the groſſeſt kind, and which do <hi>vaſtare conſcientiam,</hi> wound and waſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as Murther, Treaſon, Sacrilege, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Brethren, the Orthodox right meaning of the diſtinction is, in ſum this: ſins are ſaid to be mortall, or veniall, either in their own naturall merit, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, or elſe in the event, and iſſue: If we look to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall merit of every ſin, yea though it be but a<note n="l" place="margin">Pro. 24 9.</note> thought of fooliſhnes, it is mortall, deſerving the curſe, <hi>Gal:</hi> 3.10. and eternal death, <hi>Rom:</hi> 6.23. Yet in the event, and iſſue, ſome ſins are veniall, that is, capable of pardon, yea, all and every ſin incident into the elect, and into the adopted Sons, and Daughters of God; murther, and adultry, ſins mortal by deſert, yet veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and actually<note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 12.13.</note> pardoned to <hi>David</hi> in the event, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Perſon was accepted into favour with God; Blaſphemy, and perſecution, ſins mortall in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, yet both theſe, in the event<note n="n" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.13.</note> pardoned unto Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> being a<note n="o" place="margin">Act. 9.15.</note> choſen veſſel of ſalvation unto God; ſo was <hi>Peters</hi> perjury, and the deniall of his Maſter; yea, univerſally all ſins, all<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 12.31.</note> manner of ſins, of what kind ſoever, are pardonable to Gods elect by Chriſt, yea
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:38129:32"/>actually al pardoned to them who are really, &amp; indeed incorporate into Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rom:</hi> 8.2. And ſurely, (Beloved) Chriſt teaching us that we our ſelves ſhould forgive untill<note n="r" place="margin">Matt: 18 22</note> ſeventy times ſeven times, after a ſort, gives us notice, (as a great<note n="s" place="margin">By <hi>Andr: Ser</hi> on <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.23.</note> Divine obſerves) that He will not ſtick with us for the like number of ours; for God forbid we ſhould imagine, 'that he taught us to be more mercifull, than he will be himſelf: that number ſaith He, amounteth to ten Jubilees of pardon, for ſo many ſins we may hope for pardon at his hands: If thoſe be not enough, we have example of one whoſe ſins were more in number, than the hairs of his head: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.12. to whom yet all were remitted.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is affirmed, (and that moſt truly) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.25. by the Apoſtle, <hi>that the weaknes of God is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then men;</hi> if there were any ſin greater, than could be remitted, then the weaknes of man (for of that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſin) ſhould be ſtronger than God, which neither reaſon, nor religion will admit. And indeed, what is it in the ſins of the elect, and regenerate, that ſhould make them apprehend other, than a pardonablenes in it? In ſin are conſiderable, either the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Law, 1 Joh. 3.4. but all that tranſgreſſion is forgiven, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 32.1. or the pollution, 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 7.1. and that is covered, and<note n="v" place="margin">1 Joh. 1. 7 Rev: 1: 5. and Rev: 7.14. zech: 13.1.</note> cleanſed, or the guilt thereof, through the offence of God, and behold, neither is that at all imputed to them, <hi>ver.</hi> 2.16. as the blood of the paſchall Lamb wherewith the two ſide-poſts, and the upper dore poſt of the Houſe, wherein it was to be eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, <hi>Exod:</hi> 12: 7. (in tipe of Chriſt the true Paſſeover, as he is ſtiled: 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.7.) was ſtriken, ſaved the owners from the ſtroak of the deſtroying Angel; ſo doth the blood of ſprinkling<note n="w" place="margin">1 Pet: 1. 2 Heb. 12.24</note> of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſus Chriſt, cleanſe the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience from dead works, <hi>Heb:</hi> 9.14.</p>
            <p>To conclude, if our ſins be as<note n="x" place="margin">Mat: 7.3.</note> moats in our eyes, and cauſe them to water. Loe, God hath his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kercheif, wherewith He wipes all tears from our eyes,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:38129:32"/>
               <hi>Rev:</hi> 7.7: are they<note n="y" place="margin">Iſa: 64.6.</note> menſtruous? he hath his hyſop, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to waſh, and to make us clean, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 51.7. If they be of<note n="z" place="margin">Iſa: 1.18.</note> a ſcarlet dye, yet He hath his<note n="a" place="margin">Mal: 3.2.</note> fullers ſope to whiten the Conſcience as white as ſnow, when our Saviour in the Garden ſweat but<note n="b" place="margin">Luk: 22.44</note> [like] unto blood, it was a great agony, it made ſuch a ſweat, as was meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious; yet this was but a preparative to his potion on the Croſſe, for there He ſweat not [like] unto blood, but<note n="c" place="margin">Joh. 19.34.</note> blood and water, water to waſh away the ſins of our daily infirmities, and blood to purge our ſins in grain, and a deeper colour then blood our ſins cannot bear: ſhall we ſin (ſaith the Holy Ghoſt) that Grace may abound? God forbid: Rom. 6.1. yet if ſin do chance to abound, free grace hath the ſuperlative of ſin, and doth ſuperabound: <hi>abundat delictum, ſuperabundat gracia,</hi> Sin doth abound, but grace hath abounded above, it doth ſuperabound; Rom. 5.20. <hi>Abyſſus abyſſum invocat,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>one deep calleth for another,</hi> the depth of our ſins, for the depth of Gods compaſſions which never fail. And now, O that the Spirit of the Lord would give this Doctrine entrance into the hearts of all his People, and that the<note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 1.18. Act: 26.18.</note> eyes of their underſtanding were as bright as the Sun, that they might throughly ſee, and know the riches of the glorious inheritance of the Saints in light; who though they ſometimes fall, yet ſhall they not, can they not fall utterly away from God though the wicked one may tempt them, yet ſhall he not touch them, <hi>tactu qualitativo,</hi> as <hi>Caietan</hi> expounds it, with a touch of finall hurt, ſo dangerouſly to annoy them, as wholly to alter their renewed hearts unto a ſtate of total depravation, or corrupt impenitency, they ſhall not, they<note n="e" place="margin">1 Joh. 3.9.</note> cannot (under ſuch a ſtate of Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) ſin unto death: Behold Chriſt, whoſe ſuit God never denyed: Joh: 11: 42. He hath prayed his Father to keep them through his own name: Joh: 17.11. and his Father is greater then all, and none is able to pluck them out of his Fathers hand, no nor out of his own
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:38129:33"/>hand, <hi>Joh:</hi> 28, 29. He hath kept them all in his Fathers name, and hath not loſt one of all whom his Father had given to him, Joh: 17.12. and (which is more ſtill) what Chriſt by his merit wrought [for] them, the ſame by his Spirit he virtually worketh [in] them, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables them through his ſtrength, <hi>Phil:</hi> 4.13. in ſome meaſure, to keep themſelves under the right uſe of the lawfull means, 1 Joh. 5.18. for to our own ſafety, our own ſedulity is required; yes, (that I may cloſe up all with comfort, and leave ſome<note n="f" place="margin">Joel 2.14.</note> bleſſing from Heaven to Gods Saints behind me, that my lips like the Spouſe of Chriſt may drop as the<note n="g" place="margin">Cant 4.11.</note> Hony comb, wherein there is both <hi>mel, &amp; cera,</hi> Hony to ſweeten, and with all wax to enlighten) all you, (my Dearly Beloved Countrymen, and<note n="h" place="margin">Phil. 4.1.</note> longed for in the Lord) you who are born of God, you ſhall be all kept by Gods<note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.5.</note> own power through faith, and ſalvation, be all<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 75.24.</note> guided by his Counſel, and at laſt be brought home to his Glory. Even ſo be it, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="afterword">
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:38129:33"/>
            <head>A word to the preſent Occaſion, and ſo an end.</head>
            <p>IT may now be expected, happily on ſome hands, that I ſhould take upon me to exhort theſe learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, reverend, and religious<note n="*" place="margin">The R. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable <hi>John Wilde,</hi> Lord chief Baron of the Court of Excheq; &amp; the R. H. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Atkins</hi> one of the Juſtices of the Court of Common Pleas.</note> Judges, but truly I dare not make ſo bold; I can ſay it upon my owne knowledg of them, that they are ſuch as who do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire to<note n="a" place="margin">Acts 13.36.</note> ſerve God in their generation<note n="b" place="margin">3 John 5.:</note> faithfully, (within their ſtation) and to doe all<note n="*" place="margin">Dout. 1.17.</note> impartiall Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice even for<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 23.3.</note> Juſtice ſake; What the Scriptures (out of which I muſt have ordered my ſpeech unto them) direct for the Work, and Duty of ſuch Eminent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, their Practiſe is an exact Comment upon it: Wherefore, let us all (I am ſure the men of my profeſſion have great reaſon ſo to do) bleſſe God (by whoſe providence, and<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> power they ſit in Judgment) for them, end enlarge our<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim 2.2.</note> devotiont for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and continuation of them: They will obſerve what is ſaid in my Text; that as there is a ſinne unto Death, ſo alſo a ſin not unto Death, and will them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as<note n="d" place="margin">Exo. 22.28. Pſal. 82.6. Joh. 10.34, 35.</note> Gods with Men) temper Mercy with Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>As to M.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>M.</hi> George Luttrell <hi>of</hi> Dunſter <hi>Caſtle <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </hi>
               </note> High Sheriff, he, as he is deſcended of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of a good extraction, ſo he is an honorer of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, as is conſpicuous to all who view this goodly <hi>Poſſe Comitatus</hi> now in his Retinew, many of quality; lovers (as himſelfe, who cannot but be a Leader therein) of the right Religion, of the purity of Gods Ordinances, and of their Countrey: He will not but enoble himſelfe by doing acts worthy of his ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in advancing the glory of God, in his Perſon, in his Family, and before all; that ſo ſtriving as <hi>Boaz,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:38129:34"/>to doe<note n="e" place="margin">Ruth 4.11.</note> worthily in <hi>Ephrata,</hi> he ſhall be famous in his <hi>Bethlehem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the grand Jury, upon your fidelity and truſt, almoſt the whole tranſaction of this ſolemn, publique meeting reſteth: Gentlemen, men of good<note n="f" place="margin">Acts 6.3.</note> report, and repute, men of<note n="g" place="margin">Exo. 8.21.</note> truth, and fearing God will doe like themſelves, be tender of Gods honour, by a ſtrict enquiry after the Blaſphemers of Gods name, his precious Ordinances, Goſpel, and worſhip, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is contrary to the life, and power of godlineſſe, or to the peace, and proſperity of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: But if indeed I might ſet a ſpeciall Accent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my intimations to them, it ſhall be with the moſt ſharpeſt perſpicacity to make a diſquiſition, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of thoſe grand Incendiaries of the Chrſtian world, the brood of Jeſuites, who like Serpents<note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.6.</note> creep into every angle, and under variety of ſhapes, into moſt Aſſemblies in the Land, having <hi>Jeſus</hi> in their<note n="i" place="margin">Rev. 9.11.</note> Name, and lips, but <hi>Abaddon,</hi> and <hi>Apollyon</hi> in their hearts: In my conſcience, I am perſwaded, they have been inſtrumentally (though in a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Pet 2.1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hoc eſt, fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im, clam, &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole ſubintrodu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemi ſpeciem pietatrs, &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men eccleſiae proetendens fraudulenter &amp; <hi>Gerh</hi> &amp; <hi>Auretius</hi> ad locum.</note> clandeſtine, and imperceptible way) the rayſers and fomenters of the greateſt part of all the rufull diviſions, and diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that have been among us: I have heard ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of quality ſay, That moſt of the Engliſh Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries abroad are become empty, that perhaps, there may be the more Emiſſaries to deceive at home, God of his goodneſſe unmasque them, thoſe ſecret<note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.14.</note> Satans transformed like to Angels of light, and deliver<note n="l" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.13.</note> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſouls.</p>
            <p>As to the petty Jurers, Witneſſes, and others em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployd in the preſent publique affayres, be adviſed, and<note n="m" place="margin">2 Chr. 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed what yee doe;</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.10.</note> Perjury the God of Truth will not hold<note n="o" place="margin">Exo. 20.2.</note> guiltleſs; remember, it's a degree, and a great ſtep towards this ſin unto Death, to offend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt knowledge, chiefly if it be of malicious wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe (as ye heard but now) diſtinguiſh between the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:38129:34"/>Perſon and the<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 9.4.</note> Cauſe, know, <hi>God will not be</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>mock<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, He is</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">John 2.24, 25. &amp; John 21.17. Ier. 23, 24. Pſal. 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>omniſcient,</hi> views your moſt ſecret purpoſes, aimes, and<note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 139.1, 2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.4.</note> intentions; He is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petus</hi> once ſaid to <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> and underſtanding full of many eyes; labour then to be affected with the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration thereof, and be as the Sun and Moon in the Heavens,<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 89.36, 37.</note> faithfull witneſſes,<note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.13.</note> quit your ſelves like<note n="w" place="margin">Heb. 13.18.</note> honeſt men, and conſcientious Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>To all the people of God in generall I ſay,<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 37.27. 1 Pet. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Eſchew euill, doe good,</hi> which two make up a true <hi>Nathanael,</hi> and an Iſraelite<note n="y" place="margin">John 1.47</note> indeed; as yet, the<note n="z" place="margin">Revel. 2.5.</note> Candleſtick of the Church is among us, and<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5.15, 16.</note> lights ſhining in the ſame, O<note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 5.35.</note> rejoyce in thoſe lights whilſt they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you; Commit not by your<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 21.43.</note> unfruitfulneſſe, or unthankfulneſſe, <hi>that the Kingdome of heaven be taken from you:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 30.21. 1 Theſ. 5.20.</note> Cheriſh grace by thoſe ſanctified meanes by which the Lord at firſt conveyed it into your hearts, owne, and<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 2.29. 1 Theſ. 5 12, 13.</note> honour thoſe<note n="f" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.12.</note> allowed pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique inſtruments, who as the Lords<note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> Ambaſſadors brought the<note n="h" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.7.</note> treaſure of the<note n="i" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.11.</note> glorious Goſpel unto you, though but in earthen Veſſels, leaſt God in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſend you a<note n="k" place="margin">Amos 8 11.</note> Famine, if not of Bread and of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet of hearing the word of the Lord, even that word of<note n="l" place="margin">Jam. 1 18.</note> truth, which is able to<note n="m" place="margin">Jam. 1.21.</note> ſave your ſoules: Take heed of ſinning againſt<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 1.32.</note> light, or againſt your owne<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 5.4. Phil. 1.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> experience of Gods goodneſſe<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 5.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> diffuſed in the Ordinances; ſhun<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 19. prayed to be delivered from preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from p. ides, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>zadah arrogano fuit,</hi>
               </note> ſpirituall pride, the inordinate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verweening, and admiration of ſelfe-excellencies, the Mother, and Nurſe of moſt, or of all ſoule-diſtempers, it's a ſin now raigning above many, it makes the ſoule moſt unlike to God, and moſt of all<note n="r" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.6.</note> like unto the Devill; yea, rather be ye<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.5.</note> cloathed with humility, and let that be<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a knot (the word here only uſed) tie humility to you, as <hi>curious</hi> women do knots on their garments for ornament.</note> your Ornament, which is both the receptacle, and conſerver of all true grace, and that wherein the Spirit, and<note n="u" place="margin">Pet. 5.10.</note> God of all grace taketh up a cheerfull and a chearing<note n="w" place="margin">Iſa. 57.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mac. Homil. 19.</note> Reſt, keeping the ſoule and conſciences from the ſin unto death.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:38129:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſo the very God of peace</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>ſanctifie you wholly: and I pray God your whole ſpirit, and ſoule, and body be preſerved blameleſſe unto the coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto whom with thee, O Father, and thine Eternall Spirit, be all prayſe, honour, and immortall glory, both now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Reader, <hi>If any faults have eſcaped the Preſſe (the Author being abſent when this pious learned Sermon was printing) thou art deſired to correct them with thy pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38129:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
